<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:space="preserve" xml:id="about_doc">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                    <title xml:lang="en">About</title>
                    <title xml:lang="it">Informazioni</title>
                    <title xml:lang="fr">Présentation</title>
                    <title xml:lang="ar">عن المشروع </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>...</authority>
                <idno type="filename">About</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p><ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0 Deed Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International</ref> License.</p>
                    <p>All citation, reuse or distribution of this work must contain a link back to DOI: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.60760/unibo/igcyrgvcyr2">https://doi.org/10.60760/unibo/igcyrgvcyr2</ref> and the filename, as well as the year of consultation.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="text" xml:id="about">
                <div xml:id="about_intro">
                    <p xml:lang="en">This second edition of the <title>Inscriptions of Greek Cyrenaica</title> (<title>IGCyr</title>) and the <title>Greek Verse Inscriptions of Cyrenaica</title> (<title>GVCyr</title>) updates two corpora published online in 2017, the first collecting all the inscriptions of Greek (VII-I centuries B.C.) Cyrenaica, the second gathering the Greek metrical texts of all periods (VI B.C.-VI A.D.). These new critical editions of inscriptions from Cyrenaica are part of the international project <title>Inscriptions of Libya</title> (<title>InsLib</title>). They now include all the inscriptions known to us in February 2024, coming from this area of the ancient Mediterranean world, assembled in a single online and open access publication.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Questa seconda edizione delle <title>Iscrizioni della Cirenaica greca</title> (<title>IGCyr</title>) e delle <title>Iscrizioni metriche greche della Cirenaica</title> (<title>GVCyr</title>) aggiorna due <foreign>corpora</foreign>, pubblicati online nel 2017, il primo di tutte le iscrizioni provenienti dalla Cirenaica greca (secoli VII-I a.C.), il secondo dei testi metrici greci di ogni epoca provenienti dalla Cirenaica (VI a.C.-VI d.C.). Queste nuove edizioni critiche delle epigrafi cirenaiche fanno parte del progetto internazionale <title>Inscriptions of Libya</title> (<title>InsLib</title>). 
                        I <foreign>corpora</foreign> comprendono ora tutte le iscrizioni conosciute fino a febbraio 2024, provenienti da questa regione del Mediterraneo antico, sono riunite in un'unica pubblicazione accessibile online.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Cette seconde édition des <title>Inscriptions de la Cyrénaïque grecque</title> (<title>IGCyr</title>) et des <title>Inscriptions métriques grecques de Cyrénaïque</title> (<title>GVCyr</title>) met à jour deux corpus publiés en ligne en 2017, le premier rassemblant toutes les inscriptions de la Cyrénaïque grecque (VII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>-I<hi rend="superscript">er</hi> siècles av. J.-C.), le second recueillant les textes métriques de toutes les périodes (VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> s. av. J.-C. – VI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> s. ap. J.-C.). Ces nouvelles éditions critiques des inscriptions de Cyrénaïque font partie du projet international <title>Inscriptions of Libya</title> (<title>InsLib</title>). Elles comprennent maintenant toutes les inscriptions connues en février 2024, provenant de cette région de la Méditerranée antique, réunies dans une publication unique en ligne, en accès libre.</p>
                <p xml:lang="ar">
نقوش كيرينايكي الإغريقية (IGCyr) ونقوش الشعر الإغريقية الكيرينايكية (GVCyr)
يعد هذا العمل النسخة الثانية لنقوش كيرينايكي الإغريقية (IGCyr) ونقوش الشعر الإغريقية الكيرينايكية (GVCyr) وهو تحديث للمجموعتين المنشورتين والمتاحتين على الإنترنت منذ عام 2017: تشمل الأولى كل نقوش كيرينايكي الإغريقية من القرن السابع إلى الاول قبل الميلاد، وتحتوي الثانية على النصوص الشعرية الإغريقية لجميع الفترات الإغريقية والرومانية (القرن السادس ق.م. – القرن السادس الميلادي)، وتعتبر هذه النسخ ا الجديدة لمهمة للنقوش الكيرينايكية جزء من المشروع الدولي، نقوش ليبيا  Inscriptions of Libya (InsLib)، وتشمل الآن المعلومة لدينا حتى فبراير 2024، جاءت من هذه المنطقة من عالم البحر الأبيض المتوسط القديم، وتم تجميعها ونشرها معًا ومتاحة عبر شبكة الإنترنت.
</p></div>
                
                <div xml:id="about_toc">
                    <p xml:lang="en">In this section you will find general information about the project <title>IGCyr</title>-<title>GVCyr</title>. First of all the origin of the project and the history of its evolution into the wider international project <title>Inscriptions of Libya</title> (<title>InsLib</title>) are presented; secondly the composition of the corpora and the specifics of the digital edition are described; next you will find a sketch of the history of Greek Cyrenaica; then an outline of the history of scholarship regarding archaeological and epigraphic research about Cyrenaica.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">In questa sezione si trovano le informazioni introduttive e generali sul progetto <title>IGCyr</title>-<title>GVCyr</title>. In primo luogo è presentato il progetto nella sua genesi e nella sua appartenenza al progetto internazionale <title>Inscriptions of Libya</title> (<title>InsLib</title>); in secondo luogo si descrivono la composizione dei due <foreign>corpora</foreign> e le specifiche della pubblicazione digitale; in terzo luogo si tratteggia una breve storia della Cirenaica greca; in ultimo è delineata la storia degli studi archeologici ed epigrafici sulla Cirenaica.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Dans cette section, on trouvera des informations générales sur le projet <title>IGCyr</title>-<title>GVCyr</title>: d'abord, une présentation des origines du projet et de son développement au sein du projet international <title>Inscriptions of Libya</title> (<title>InsLib</title>); ensuite une description de la structure des corpus et des spécificités de l'édition digitale; enfin une brève histoire de la Cyrénaïque grecque et un historique des recherches archéologiques et épigraphiques sur la Cyrénaïque.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">عن المشروع 
يوجد في هذا القسم معلومات عامة عن مشروع IGCyr-GVCyr. أولاً: تقديم لأصل المشروع وتاريخ تطوره ليدخل في الإطار العام الأوسع، نقوش ليبيا (InsLib). ثانياً: وصف محتوى المجموعتين وتفاصيل النسخة الرقمية. يلي ذلك عرضًا ملخصاً لتاريخ كيرينايكي الإغريقةن ثم موجزاً لتاريخ الدراسات المتعلقة بالبحوث الأثرية والكتابات المنقوشة حول إقليم كيرينايكي.</p>
                    
                    <list xml:id="about-toc">
                        <item><ref target="about.html#project">
                        <seg xml:lang="en">The project</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="it">Il progetto</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="fr">Le projet</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="ar">المشروع</seg>
                    </ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="about.html#igcyr2_gvcyr2">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> | GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="about.html#greek_cyrenaica">
                        <seg xml:lang="en">Greek Cyrenaica</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="it">La Cirenaica greca</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="fr">La Cyrénaïque grecque</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="ar"> كيرينايكي الإغريقية</seg>
                        </ref></item>
                    <item><ref target="about.html#scholarship">
                        <seg xml:lang="en">Scholarship</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="it">Storia degli studi</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="fr">Historique des recherches</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="ar">الدراسات</seg>
                        </ref></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                
                <div xml:id="project">
                    <head>
                        <seg xml:lang="en">The project</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="it">Il progetto</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="fr">Le projet</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="ar">المشروع</seg>
                    </head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">A comprehensive corpus of the inscriptions of Greek Cyrenaica was a longstanding desideratum among the scholars of the ancient world. Greek inscriptions from Archaic, Classical and Hellenistic Cyrenaica were up to 2017 scattered among many different, sometimes outdated publications, while new texts had been discovered and edited in between. After the launching of the 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> edition, some errors were detected, new finds and some neglected fragments were available for addition, further studies were published, making a second edition desirable. Moreover, with the new tool EFES, implementing a digital epigraphical corpus was made much easier.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In 2011 Catherine Dobias-Lalou, who has been a member of the French archaeological mission in Libya since 1976 and has been studying the inscriptions of the Greek period since 1970, agreed to edit a comprehensive epigraphic corpus in EpiDoc with the collaboration of scholars from the University of Bologna (Lucia Criscuolo, Alice Bencivenni) and the University of Macerata (Simona Antolini, Silvia Maria Marengo, Gianfranco Paci).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In the same year the <title>Inscriptions of Greek Cyrenaica</title> (<title>IGCyr</title>) project became part of the wider international <title>Inscriptions of Libya</title> (<title>InsLib</title>) project, incorporating <title>Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania</title> (at the time already available online as <title><ref target="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/">IRT 2009</ref></title>, and now enhanced as <title><ref target="http://irt2021.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/">IRT 2021</ref></title>), the <title>Inscriptions of Roman Cyrenaica</title> project (at the time in preparation and launched online as <title><ref target="https://ircyr2020.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/">IRCyr2020</ref></title>), and the ostraka from Bu Ngem (already available on the website <ref target="http://papyri.info/">Papyri.info</ref> and now incorporated into <title>IRT 2021</title>). The collaborative undertaking was agreed upon between Charlotte Roueché, Catherine Dobias-Lalou and Lucia Criscuolo in May 2011 and involves the Universities of Bologna (Dipartimento di Storia Culture Civiltà), Macerata (Dipartimento di Studi umanistici), Sorbonne-Université Lettres (Centre de recherche sur la Libye antique) and King's College London (Centre for Hellenic Studies and Department of Digital Humanities).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Since then the thematic corpus <title>Greek Verse inscriptions of Cyrenaica</title> (<title>GVCyr</title>) has been designed as a corpus cutting across <title>IGCyr</title> and <title>IRCyr</title>. It includes Greek metrical texts from both the Greek and the Roman periods in Cyrenaica. An essential addition to the <title>IGCyr</title> and <title>GVCyr</title> corpora, as well as a natural outcome of the study of the inscriptions, is the planned publication of the <title>Prosopographia Cyrenaica</title>.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Alice Bencivenni (rev. Charlotte Roueché)</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="it">Da tempo gli studiosi del mondo antico avvertivano la mancanza di un <foreign>corpus</foreign> completo delle iscrizioni della Cirenaica greca, che come tale non era mai stato realizzato. Le iscrizioni greche della Cirenaica arcaica, classica ed ellenistica si trovavano, in effetti, fino al 2017 disperse in molte pubblicazioni differenti e talvolta poco accessibili. 
                        Alcune edizioni di questi documenti erano, inoltre, ormai superate e numerosi nuovi testi si erano aggiunti nel tempo alla conoscenza della comunità scientifica.
                    Dopo la pubblicazione online della prima edizione, sono stati individuati errori, nuovi ritrovamenti e frammenti precedentemente tralasciati erano in attesa di essere aggiunti, nuovi studi sono stati pubblicati, rendendo auspicabile una seconda edizione. In aggiunta, la creazione di EFES ha reso molto più semplice l’implementazione di un <foreign>corpus</foreign> epigrafico digitale.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Nel 2011 Catherine Dobias-Lalou, che è membro della missione archeologica francese in Libia dal 1976 e ne ha studiato le iscrizioni greche fin dal 1970, ha accettato di curare l'edizione critica di un <foreign>corpus</foreign> in EpiDoc delle epigrafi greche cirenaiche in collaborazione con studiosi delle Università di Bologna (Lucia Criscuolo, Alice Bencivenni) e Macerata (Silvia Maria Marengo, Gianfranco Paci), è stato compiuto un importante passo avanti nella storia degli studi sulla Libia antica.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Nello stesso anno il progetto <title>Inscriptions of Greek Cyrenaica</title> (<title>IGCyr</title>) è diventato parte del più ampio progetto internazionale <title>Inscriptions of Libya</title> (<title>InsLib</title>), che comprende le <title>Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania</title> (all’epoca già online come <title><ref target="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/">IRT 2009</ref></title> e ora aggiornato in <title><ref target="http://irt2021.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/">IRT 2021</ref></title>), il progetto <title>Inscriptions of Roman Cyrenaica</title> (allora in preparazione e ora online come <title><ref target="https://ircyr2020.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/">IRCyr2020</ref></title>), e gli ostraka da Bu Ngem (già disponibili sul sito <ref target="http://papyri.info/">Papyri.info</ref> e ora incorporati in <title>IRT 2021</title>). 
                        La collaborazione scientifica è stata siglata tra Charlotte Roueché, Catherine Dobias-Lalou e Lucia Criscuolo nel maggio del 2011 e coinvolge le Università di Bologna (Dipartimento di Storia Culture Civiltà), Macerata (Dipartimento di Studi umanistici), Sorbonne-Université Lettres (Centre de recherche sur la Libye antique) e il King's College London (Centre for Hellenic Studies e Department of Digital Humanities).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">In seguito è stato progettato anche il <foreign>corpus</foreign> tematico <title>Greek Verse inscriptions of Cyrenaica</title> (<title>GVCyr</title>), che nasce come raccolta trasversale tra <title>IGCyr</title> e <title>IRCyr</title>. Comprende i testi metrici greci della Cirenaica greca e romana. Un completamento essenziale per i due <foreign>corpora</foreign> <title>IGCyr</title> e <title>GVCyr</title>, nonché un esito naturale dello studio condotto sulle iscrizioni, è, infine, la progettata pubblicazione della <title>Prosopographia Cyrenaica</title>.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Alice Bencivenni</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="fr">On ressentait depuis longtemps le besoin d'un corpus complet des inscriptions de la Cyrénaïque grecque, mais sa réalisation n'avait jamais été menée à bien. Les inscriptions grecques de la Cyrénaïque archaïque, classique et hellénistique se trouvaient en effet jusqu’en 2017 dispersées dans de nombreuses publications différentes, souvent peu accessibles et parfois dépassées, tandis que de nombreux textes nouveaux avaient été découverts et publiés entre temps. 
                        Après la mise en ligne de la première édition, des erreurs ont été repérées, de nouvelles trouvailles, ainsi que des fragments laissés de côté, attendaient d’être ajoutés, de nouvelles études ont été publiées, rendant souhaitable une seconde édition. En outre, la création de l’outil EFES rendait beaucoup plus aisée la mise en œuvre d’un corpus épigraphique numérique.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">En 2011 Catherine Dobias-Lalou, qui est membre de la mission archéologique française en Libye depuis 1976 et s'est intéressée aux inscriptions grecques de la région depuis 1970, avait accepté de se charger de l'édition critique d'un corpus EpiDoc des inscriptions grecques de Cyrénaïque en collaboration avec des chercheurs de l'Université de Bologne (Lucia Criscuolo, Alice Bencivenni) et de Macerata (Silvia Maria Marengo, Gianfranco Paci).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">La même année, le projet <title>Inscriptions of Greek Cyrenaica</title> (<title>IGCyr</title>) s'est inséré dans le plus vaste projet international <title>Inscriptions of Libya</title> (<title>InsLib</title>), qui comprend les <title>Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania</title> (à l’époque déjà disponibles sous la forme des <title><ref target="http://inslib.kcl.ac.uk/irt2009/">IRT 2009</ref></title> et maintenant mises à jour dans <title><ref target="http://irt2021.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/">IRT 2021</ref></title>), le projet <title>Inscriptions of Roman Cyrenaica</title> (alors en préparation et mis en ligne comme <title><ref target="https://ircyr2020.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/">IRCyr2020</ref></title>) et les ostraka de Bu Ngem (déjà disponibles sur le site <ref target="http://papyri.info/">Papyri.info</ref> et aujourd’hui incorporés dans <title>IRT 2021</title>). 
                        Un accord de collaboration scientifique a été passé entre Charlotte Roueché, Catherine Dobias-Lalou et Lucia Criscuolo en mai 2011 et regroupe les Universités de Bologne (Dipartimento di Storia Culture Civiltà), de Macerata (Dipartimento di Studi umanistici), de Sorbonne-Université Lettres (Centre de recherche sur la Libye antique) et le King's College de Londres (Centre for Hellenic Studies et Department of Digital Humanities).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Par la suite, s'est ajouté au projet le corpus thématique <title>Greek Verse inscriptions of Cyrenaica</title> (<title>GVCyr</title>), qui est conçu comme un recueil transversal entre les <title>IGCyr</title> et les <title>IRCyr</title>. Il comprend les textes métriques grecs de la Cyrénaïque grecque et romaine. En complément essentiel des deux corpus <title>IGCyr</title> et <title>GVCyr</title> et découlant naturellement des travaux menés sur les inscriptions, la publication d'une <title>Prosopographia Cyrenaica</title> est en préparation.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Alice Bencivenni (trad. Catherine Dobias-Lalou)</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="ar">المجموعة الشاملة لنقوش كيرينايكي الإغريقية كانت مُبتغًا لطالما راود عقول البُحاث في التاريخ القديم. إن نقوش كيرينايكي الاغريقية التي تعود إلى العصرالآرخي والكلاسيكي ثم الهللينيستسي كانت  حتى عام 2017 مُبعثرة  في منشورات مختلفة بعضها عفا عليها الزمن، في حين أن النصوص الجديدة المكتشفة قد رُجعت وثقت بشكل أفضل.
بعد نشر النسخة الأولى تبينت لنا وجود بعض الأخطاء وتوفرت لنا بعض الاكتشافات الجديدة وأصبح من الممكن إضافة بعض الأجزاء المهملة. إضافة إلى ذلك فإن نشر المزيد من الدراسات جعل من العمل على إخراج الطبعة الثانية أمر مرغوب فيه. علاوة على ذلك، مع وجود وسائل التنولوجيا الجديدة EFES" أصبح  إعداد مجموعة كتابية رقمية أسهل بكثير.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">في عام 2011 وافقت كاثرين دوبياس-لالو (Catherine Dobias-Lalou)- التي كانت عضواً في البعثة الأثرية الفرنسية في ليبيا منذ عام 1976 وكانت تعكف على دراسة نقوش الفترة الإغريقية منذ عام 1970- على إعداد مجموعة  كتابية شاملة في (ترميز وتوثيق النقوش EpiDoc) بالتعاون مع باحثين من جامعة بولونا Bologna وهم لوتشيا كريسكولو Lucia Criscuolo و أليس بينسيفيني  Alice Bencivenni وكذلك سيلفيا ماريا مارينقو Silvia Maria Marengo  و جيانفرانكو باتشي Gianfranco Paci  من  جامعة ماشيراتا Macerata بالإضافة إلي سيمونا أنتوليني Simona Antolini من جامعة روما تور فيرقاتا Roma Tor Vergata.</p>
                   <p xml:lang="ar">وفي العام نفسه أصبحت نقوش كيرينايكي الإغريقية (IGCyr) جزءاً من مشروع النقوش الليبية الدولي Inscriptions of Libya (InsLib) ، الذي يشمل نقوش تريبوليتانيا الرومانية (IRT) Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania ، المتاح حالياً على الإنترنت،  (حيث أشير إليه بهذا الاختصار ] [IRT 2009] ولكنه الان تحت الاختصار [IRT2021]  ومشروع نقوش كيرينايكي الرومانية، )الذي كان تحت الاإنجاز في ذلك الوقت وهو الآن متاح على شبكة الإنترنت تحت هذا الاختصار [IRCyr2020])، وشقف الفخار التي عليها كتابات (ostraka) من حصن بونجيم Ngem Bu (متاح حالياً على موقع [Papyri.info]) والآن دُمج مع [IRT2021]. في مايو 2011 أجرى اتفاق على مشروع تعاوني بين عدة أطراف وهم شارلوت روشي Charlotte Roueché  وكاثرين دوبياس -لالو  Dobias-Lalou Catherine ولوسيا كريسكولو Lucia Criscuolo  وشمل ايضاً جامعة بولونا (Dipartimento di Storia Culture Civiltà) وجامعة ماشيراتا (Dipartimento di Studi umanistici) وجامعة السوربون الرابعة بباريس (Centre de recherche sur la Libye antique) بالإضافة إلى كينقس كوليج بلندن (Centre for Hellenic Studies and Departme nt of Digital Humanities).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">ومنذ ذلك الحين، صُممت مجموعة نقوش الشعر الإغريقية الكيرينايكية (GVCyr) منفصلة عن مجموعة  نقوش كيرينايكي الإغريقية (IGCyr). وهي تحتوي النصوص الشعرية الإغريقية لكل من الفترين الإغريقية والرومانية في كيرينايكي. و كإضافة أساسية لمجموعتي  IGCyr  وGVCyr  وكذلك كنتيجة طبيعية لدراسة النقوش  فقد أعدت خطة  لنشر Prosopographia Cyrenaica Prosopographia] تعني البحث أو التحقيق في المميزات العامة لمجموعة تنتمي لفترة تاريخية معينة].  (إعداد: أليس بينسيفيني. مراجعة: شارلوت روشي. ترجمة: منى عبدالحميد)</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">Alice Bencivenni (rev. Charlotte Roueché; translated by Muna Abdelhamed)</p>
                </div>
                
                <div xml:id="igcyr2_gvcyr2">
                    <head>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> | GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The <title>IGCyr</title> corpus assembled 920 inscriptions from Greek Cyrenaica (VII-I centuries B.C.). Most of these inscriptions had been published previously, sometimes in versions which could be improved, while 125 of them were unpublished. 
                        <title>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> now provides 955 inscriptions, with 43 new items and 8 deleted ones, which are now considered fragments belonging to other inscriptions or to another period. Among the new entries, 29 are unpublished.  The <title>GVCyr</title> corpus assembled 56 Greek metrical inscriptions from Greek and Roman Cyrenaica; 48 out of them had been published already, but they had never been studied together. <title>GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> has now 59 entries, with 1 unpublished fragment. The old numbers have not changed, the new entries have new numbers. A large amount of new Arabic translations appears for the first time in this edition.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Most of these texts have been re-read by Catherine Dobias-Lalou, who as a member of the French archaeological mission in Libya from 1976 was able to examine most of the material available in Shahat (Cyrene), Susa (Apollonia) and paid shorter visits to Tulmaytha (Ptolemais), Tocra (Taucheira), Benghazi (Euesperides/Berenike) and other locations. Further improvements have been provided by Gianfranco Paci and Silvia Maria Marengo, who have both studied the inscriptions from Cyrenaica for many years; it has also been possible to draw on the archive of earlier epigraphists of the Italian mission held by the University of Macerata. 
                        <title>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> now takes advantage of new issues by Emilio Rosamilia (Mission of the University of Urbino), both published and unpublished, and of the newest results of the mission of the University of Chieti, headed by Oliva Menozzi (Stefano Struffolino for epigraphy). The <title>GVCyr</title> corpus, where texts from the Greek period are not the most numerous, profited from Joyce Reynolds' documentation, including some unpublished items. For <title>GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> we add two recent finds and a formerly neglected fragment. 
                        Documents that are both prose and verse have been inserted into the <title>GVCyr</title> corpus (except for <ref target=".././gvcyr033">GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 033</ref> and <ref target=".././igcyr097100">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 097100</ref>, which are distinct entries; the same for <ref target=".././gvcyr042">GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 042</ref> and <ref target="https://ircyr2020.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/en/inscriptions/C.415.html"><title>IRCyr2020</title> C.415</ref>). The publication, online, of all these inscriptions in one single new critical edition has been made possible by Lucia Criscuolo, Alice Bencivenni and the University of Bologna, which is hosting both editions of the <title>IGCyr</title>-<title>GVCyr</title> corpora.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The collection is made up of transcriptions, squeezes and illustrations for the majority of the texts, held in the archives of the Centre de recherche sur la Libye antique de Sorbonne-Université Lettres, in the personal archive of Catherine Dobias-Lalou and in the archives of the University of Macerata. Some of the remainder are illustrated in photographs held in the archives of the Libyan Department of Antiquities at Shahat (Cyrene) and also in the archives of other foreign missions. 
                        Furthermore Catherine Dobias-Lalou took advantage of the <title>IRCyr</title> project archive in London, which was generously put at her disposal. We did not include, as being part of other collections, the inscriptions painted on vases (see the <ref target="https://avi.unibas.ch">AVI</ref>), captions on coins and marks on amphoras and tiles.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The <title>Inscriptions of Greek Cyrenaica</title> project is publishing these materials in two online EpiDoc corpora: <title>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> and <title>GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title>, which can be consulted separately, or cross-searched. Each inscription record presents metadata description, bibliography, Greek text, apparatus, translation into modern languages (English, French, Italian and partly Arabic) and commentary, together with the fullest available collection of illustrations. 
                        The corpora are presented as two series of documents; but, as with the <title>IRT</title> and <title>IRCyr</title> corpora, they also include geographical information linking to various projects gathered on the website <ref target="http://www.slsgazetteer.org/">Heritage Gazetteer of Libya</ref> developed by the Society for Libyan Studies in London (now <ref target="https://www.bilnas.org/?ref=slsrebranded">British Institute for Libyan and Northern African Studies</ref>).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Alice Bencivenni (rev. Charlotte Roueché)</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="it">Il <foreign>corpus</foreign> <title>IGCyr</title> raccoglieva 920 iscrizioni provenienti dalla Cirenaica greca (secoli VII-I a.C.). La maggioranza di queste iscrizioni era già stata pubblicata in precedenza, talvolta in edizioni che potevano essere migliorate, mentre 125 erano inedite. 
                        <title>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> presenta ora 955 iscrizioni, totale che ne include 43 nuove e dal quale ne sono state soppresse 8 (in quanto associate ad altre iscrizioni o ricondotte ad altre epoche). Tra le nuove iscrizioni, 29 sono inedite. 
                        Il <foreign>corpus</foreign> <title>GVCyr</title> raccoglieva 56 iscrizioni metriche greche dalla Cirenaica greca e romana, di cui 8 inedite, che non erano mai state studiate insieme.
                    <title>GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> comprende 59 iscrizioni, di cui un frammento inedito. La vecchia numerazione delle iscrizioni non è cambiata, le nuove voci hanno nuovi numeri identificativi. Un buon numero di traduzioni arabe supplementari è proposto per la prima volta in questa edizione.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Una buona parte di questi testi è stata riedita da Catherine Dobias-Lalou che, come membro della missione archeologica francese in Libia, ha potuto studiare fin dal 1976 il materiale disponibile a Shahat (Cirene) e a Susa (Apollonia) e ha compiuto campagne più brevi a Tulmaytha (Ptolemais), a Tocra (Taucheira), a Benghazi (Euesperides/Berenice) e in altri centri minori. 
                        La lettura di alcuni testi è stata migliorata da Gianfranco Paci e da Silvia Maria Marengo, entrambi impegnati da tempo nello studio delle iscrizioni dalla Cirenaica, anche grazie all'apporto dell'archivio, custodito dall'Università di Macerata, che raccoglie i materiali degli epigrafisti della missione italiana. 
                        <title>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> beneficia ora di nuove acquisizioni, pubblicate e inedite, di Emilio Rosamilia, della missione dell’Università di Urbino, e delle più recenti scoperte della missione dell’Università di Chieti, guidata da Oliva Menozzi (epigrafista Stefano Struffolino).
                        Il <foreign>corpus</foreign> <title>GVCyr</title>, nel quale i testi del periodo greco non sono i più numerosi, ha potuto usufruire della documentazione di Joyce Reynolds, comprendente un certo numero di inediti. Aggiungiamo a <title>GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> due ritrovamenti recenti e un frammento precedentemente trascurato. 
                        Le iscrizioni composte di una parte in prosa e una parte in versi sono state inserite nel <foreign>corpus</foreign> <title>GVCyr</title> (fatta eccezione per <ref target=".././gvcyr033">GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 033</ref> e <ref target=".././igcyr097100">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 097100</ref>, che formano due voci distinte, e per <ref target=".././gvcyr042">GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 042</ref> e <ref target="https://ircyr2020.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/en/inscriptions/C.415.html"><title>IRCyr2020</title> C.415</ref>). 
                        La pubblicazione di tutte queste iscrizioni in un'unica nuova edizione critica online è stata resa possibile grazie a Lucia Criscuolo, ad Alice Bencivenni e all'Università di Bologna, che ospita le due edizioni dei <foreign>corpora</foreign> <title>IGCyr</title>-<title>GVCyr</title>.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">La collezione comprende trascrizioni, calchi e immagini per la grande maggioranza dei testi epigrafici, conservati negli archivi del Centre de recherche sur la Libye antique della Sorbonne-Université Lettres, nell'archivio personale di Catherine Dobias-Lalou e negli archivi dell'Università di Macerata. Alcuni dei testi rimanenti sono illustrati in fotografie conservate presso gli archivi del Dipartimento libico delle Antichità di Shahat (Cirene), come pure negli archivi di altre missioni straniere. 
                        Catherine Dobias-Lalou ha potuto inoltre attingere agli archivi, generosamente messi a sua disposizione, del progetto <title>IRCyr</title> a Londra. Non sono state incluse, visto che fanno parte di altre raccolte, le iscrizioni dipinte su vaso (cf. il progetto <ref target="https://avi.unibas.ch/">AVI</ref>), le leggende monetali e i bolli su anfore e laterizi.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Il progetto <title>Inscriptions of Greek Cyrenaica</title> pubblica questo materiale sotto forma di due <foreign>corpora</foreign> digitali in EpiDoc accessibili online: <title>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> e <title>GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title>, che possono essere consultati insieme o separatamente. 
                        La scheda di ognuna delle iscrizioni presenta la descrizione dei metadati, la bibliografia, il testo greco, l'apparato critico, la traduzione (inglese, francese, italiano e, per alcune, anche arabo) e un commento, insieme al maggior numero di immagini disponibile. I nuovi <foreign>corpora</foreign> sono presentati come due serie di documenti; ma, come per i <foreign>corpora</foreign> <title>IRT</title> e <title>IRCyr</title>, essi comprendono anche informazioni geografiche collegate a vari progetti raggruppati sul sito <ref target="http://www.slsgazetteer.org/">Heritage Gazetteer of Libya</ref>, sviluppato dalla Society for Libyan Studies (ora <ref target="https://www.bilnas.org/?ref=slsrebranded">British Institute for Libyan and Northern African Studies</ref>) di Londra.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Alice Bencivenni</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Le corpus <title>IGCyr</title> rassemblait 920 inscriptions provenant de la Cyrénaïque grecque (VII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi>-I<hi rend="superscript">er</hi> s. av. J.-C.). La plus grande partie de ces inscriptions avait déjà été publiée auparavant, souvent dans des éditions qui pouvaient être améliorées, tandis que 125 étaient encore inédites. 
                        <title>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> offre maintenant 955 inscriptions, avec 43 nouveaux numéros et 8 supprimés, parce qu’ils sont rattachés à d’autres inscriptions ou à d’autres périodes. Parmi les nouvelles entrées, 29 sont inédites. 
                        Le corpus <title>GVCyr</title> rassemblait 56 inscriptions métriques de la Cyrénaïque grecque et romaine, dont 8 inédits; jamais on ne les avait étudiées ensemble.
                    <title>GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> comprend 59 inscriptions, dont un fragment inédit. Les anciens numéros n’ont pas changé, les nouvelles entrées ont des numéros nouveaux. Un bon nombre de traductions arabes supplémentaires est donné pour la première fois dans cette édition.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Ces textes ont été révisés en grande partie par Catherine Dobias-Lalou qui, comme membre de la mission archéologique française en Libye, a travaillé sur le terrain depuis 1976, étudiant tout le matériel disponible à Shahat (Cyrène) et à Susa (Apollonia) et effectuant des inspections plus rapides à Tulmaytha (Ptolemais), à Tocra (Taucheira), à Benghazi (Euhespérides/Bérénikè) et sur d'autres sites mineurs. La lecture de certains textes a été améliorée par Gianfranco Paci et Silvia Maria Marengo, tous deux versés depuis longtemps dans l'étude des inscriptions de la Cyrénaïque et bénéficiant en outre des archives conservées à l'Université de Macerata, qui rassemble les matériaux des épigraphistes de la mission italienne. 
                        <title>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> profite maintenant de nouveaux progrès, publiés et inédits, dus à Emilio Rosamilia, de la mission de l’Université d’Urbino, et des plus récentes découvertes de la mission de l’Université de Chieti, dirigée par Oliva Menozzi (épigraphiste Stefano Struffolino). 
                        Le corpus <title>GVCyr</title>, où les textes de la période grecque ne sont pas les plus nombreux, a bénéficié de la documentation de Joyce Reynolds, comprenant un certain nombre d'inédits. Nous ajoutons pour <title>GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> deux trouvailles récentes et un fragment précédemment négligé. 
                        Les documents comprenant une partie en prose et une partie métrique ont été insérés dans le corpus <title>GVCyr</title> (à l'exception de <ref target=".././gvcyr033">GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 033</ref> et <ref target=".././igcyr097100">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 097100</ref> qui forment deux entrées, de même que <ref target=".././gvcyr042">GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi> 042</ref> et <ref target="https://ircyr2020.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/en/inscriptions/C.415.html"><title>IRCyr2020</title> C.415</ref>). 
                        La publication de toutes ces inscriptions en une nouvelle édition critique complète en ligne a été rendue possible grâce à Lucia Criscuolo, à Alice Bencivenni et à l'Université de Bologne, qui héberge deux éditions des corpus <title>IGCyr</title>-<title>GVCyr</title>.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Le recueil est fondé pour la majorité des textes épigraphiques sur des transcriptions, des estampages et des images conservés dans les archives du Centre de recherche sur la Libye antique de Sorbonne-Université Lettres, dans les archives personnelles de Catherine Dobias-Lalou et dans les archives de l'Université de Macerata. 
                        Par ailleurs, quelques inscriptions sont illustrées par des photographies conservées dans les archives du Département des Antiquités de Libye à Shahat (Cyrène), ainsi que dans les archives d’autres missions étrangères. Enfin, Catherine Dobias-Lalou a aussi pu puiser dans les archives du projet <title>IRCyr</title> à Londres, libéralement mises à sa disposition. 
                        On a laissé de côté, parce qu'elles relèvent d'autres recueils, les inscriptions peintes sur les vases (voir le projet <ref target="https://avi.unibas.ch/">AVI</ref>), les légendes monétaires et les marques d'amphores et de tuiles.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Le projet <title>Inscriptions of Greek Cyrenaica</title> publie ce matériel sous la forme de deux corpus électroniques sous EpiDoc, accessibles en ligne: <title>IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title> et <title>GVCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi></title>, qu'on peut consulter à la fois ou séparément. La fiche de chaque inscription présente la description des métadonnées, la bibliographie, le texte grec, l'apparat critique, des traductions (anglaise, française, italienne et, pour certaines, arabe) et un commentaire. 
                        Les photographies, copies, estampages sont numérisés pour illustrer l'édition critique des textes épigraphiques. Les corpus sont présentés en deux ensembles distincts de documents; mais, de même que les corpus <title>IRT</title> et <title>IRCyr</title>, ils comprennent des renseignements géographiques reliés à divers projets regroupés sur le site <ref target="http://www.slsgazetteer.org/">Heritage Gazetteer of Libya</ref>, développé par la Society for Libyan Studies à Londres (désormais <ref target="https://www.bilnas.org/?ref=slsrebranded">British Institute for Libyan and Northern African Studies</ref>).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Alice Bencivenni (trad. Catherine Dobias-Lalou)</p>
                    

                <p xml:lang="ar">جمعت  IGCyrحصيلة 920 نقشًا من كيرينايكي خلال العصر الإغريقي (القرنين السابع إلى الأول ق. م.)، وتم نشر معظمها سابقًا، وأحيانًا في إصدارات يمكن تحسينها، في حين لم يتم نشر 125 منها. يوفر IGyr2 الآن 955 نقشًا، مع 43 عنصرًا جديدًا و8 تم حذفها تعتبر الآن أجزاء تنتمي إلى نقوش أخرى أو إلى فترة زمنية مختلفة، ومن بين الإدخالات الجديدة 29 منها غير منشورة. تحتوي مجموعة GVCyr على 56 نقشًا إغريقيًا لنصًا شعريًا من كيرينايكي خلال العصرين الإغريقي والروماني؛ تم بالفعل نشر 48 منها، لكن لم يتم مطلقًا دراستها معًا. يحتوي GVCyr² الآن على 59 مدخلًا، مع جزء واحد غير منشور، ولم يتم تغيير الأرقام القديمة، ومنحت الإدخالات الجديدة أرقام مداخل جديدة، وتظهر في هذه الطبعة ولأول مرة قدر كبير من التراجم العربية الجديدة.</p>



                    <p xml:lang="ar">تمت إعادة قراءة معظم هذه النصوص من قبل كاثرين دوبياس لالو Catherine Dobias-Lalou التي تمكنت من خلال صفتها عضوًا في البعثة الأثرية الفرنسية في ليبيا منذ عام 1976، من فحص معظم المواد المتوفرة في شحات (قورينا)، وسوسة (أبولونيا) وقد قامت بزيارات قصيرة إلى طلميثة (بطوليمايس)، توكرة (تاوخيرا)، بنغازي (يوسبيريدس/بيرينيكي) ومواقع أخرى، وقد أجريت  المزيد من التحسينات بواسطة جيانفرانكو باسي Gianfranco Paci وسيلفيا ماريا مارينغو Silvia Maria Marengo اللتين درستا نقوشًا من كيرينايكي لسنوات عديدة، وكان من الممكن أيضًا الاعتماد على أرشيف النقوش لمتخصصي نقوش البعثة الإيطالية المحفوظ في جامعة ماشيراتا Macerata. استفادت IGCyr2 الآن من الإصدارات الجديدة لإميليو روزاميليا Emilio Rosamilia (بعثة جامعة أوربينو Urbino)، المنشورة وغير المنشورة، ومن أحدث النتائج المهمة التي توصلت إليها بعثة جامعة كييتي Chieti، برئاسة أوليفا مينوتزي Oliva Menozzi (ستيفانو ستروفولينو Stefano Struffolino فيما يتعلق بالنقوش)، واستفيد كذلك من مجموعة  GVCyr المنسوبة إلى وثائق جويس رينولدز Joyce Reynolds المشتملة على عدد يسير من النصوص الشعرية من الفترة الإغريقية بما في ذلك بعض العناصر غير المنشورة. بالنسبة لـ GVCyr² نضيف اكتشافين حديثين وجزءًا كان في السابق مهملًا، وتم إدراج الوثائق النثرية والشـعـرية في مجـموعة GVCyr باستثناء ]رابط إلى [GVCyr²033  ورابط إلى  IGCyr² 097100] [ وهي إدخالات متميزة؛ الشيء نفسه بالنسبة إلى الرابط إلى [GVCyr²042] والرابط إلىIRCyr20 C.415]  وتم نشر كل هذه النقوش عبر الإنترنت، في طبعة نقدية واحدة جديدة بفضل لوسيا كريسكولو Lucia Criscuolo، وأليس بينسيفيني Alice Bencivenni، وجامعة بولونيا Bologna التي تستضيف كلا الطبعتين من مجموعة  IGCyr-GVCyr.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">تتكون المجموعة من تدوينات ورسوم توضيحية لغالبية النصوص المحفوظة في أرشيفات مركز البحوث حول ليبيا القديمة في جامعة السوربون - جامعة الآداب، وفي الأرشيف الشخصي لكاثرين دوبياس لالو وفي أرشيفات جامعة ماشيراتا، وبعض ماتبقى موضح في صور ضوئية محفوظة في أرشيفات إدارة مراقبة الآثار في شحات (قورينا) وكذلك في أرشيفات البعثات الأجنبية الأخرى. علاوة على ذلك، استفادت كاثرين دوبياس لالو من أرشيف مشروع IRCyr في لندن والذي وضع بسخاء تحت تصرفها. وباعتنبار أن النقوش المرسومة على الأواني الفخارية تمثل جزءًا من من مجموعات أخرى فإنها لم تدرج هنا، انظر إلى  رابط  إلى AVI [ والتعليقات التوضيحية على العملة المعدنية والعلامات على الأمفورات والقرميد.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">ينشر مشروع نقوش كيرينايكي الإغريقية هذه المواد في مجموعتين من مجموعات EpiDoc عبر الإنترنت: IGCyr² وGVCyr²، اللتين يمكن الرجوع إليهما بشكل منفصل أو البحث عنهما بشكل مشترك، ويعرض كل سجل نقش البيانات الوصفية، وقائمة المراجع، والنص الإغريقي، والتحليل apparatus، والترجمة إلى اللغات الحديثة (الإنجليزية والفرنسية والإيطالية وجزءًا منها بالعربية)، والتعليقات، بالإضافة إلى المجموعة الكاملة المتاحة من الرسوم التوضيحية. يتم تقديم المجموعات الجديدة في سلسلتين من الوثائق؛ ولكن، كما هو الحال مع IRT ومجموعات  IRCyrفهي تتضمن أيضًا معلومات جغرافية مرتبطة بمختلف المشاريع التي تم جمعها على الموقع الإلكتروني [رابط إلى الفهرس الجغراقي لأسماء مواقع التراث الليبي Heritage Gazetteer of Libya]، الذي طورته جمعية الدراسات الليبية في لندن (الآن المعهد البريطاني للدراسات الليبية وشمال أفريقيا(Now: the British Institute of Libyan and North African Studies ‘BILNAS’)</p>

                    <p xml:lang="ar">Alice Bencivenni (rev. Charlotte Roueché, translated by Muna Abdelhamed)</p>
                </div>
                
                <div xml:id="greek_cyrenaica">
                    <head>
                        <seg xml:lang="en">Greek Cyrenaica</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="it">La Cirenaica greca</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="fr">La Cyrénaïque grecque</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="ar"> كيرينايكي الإغريقية</seg>
                    </head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Ancient Cyrenaica is the eastern coastal region of Libya, which, at least from the first century A.D., was also known as the Pentapolis, i.e. the federation of five cities (Pliny, <title>Naturalis Historia</title> 5.5.5.): these are, from west to east, Euesperides/Berenice (Benghazi), Taucheira/Arsinoe (Tocra, Tukrah), Barka/Ptolemais (Tolemaide, Tulmaytha), Cyrene (Shahat), and Apollonia (Susa). These cities were founded by Greek colonists who did not completely control their hinterland: many villages and small towns grew up in the surrounding areas leaving visible remains to this day.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">«The settled region of Cyrenaica is characterized largely by the upland plateau of the Jabal Akhdar (the Green Mountain) which projects northwards into the Mediterranean between the Gulf of Sidra (the Greater Syrtis) to the W and the low, arid coastlands of the Marmaric region towards Alexandria. The plateau rises in two steps, and while on the W there is a wide coastal strip between the foot of the jabal and Benghazi, this narrows progressively as one travels north-eastward, disappearing almost completely beyond Ptolemais. 
                        Towards the E, the land drops more gradually and as it becomes drier, so settlement is more sparse toward Tubruq. ... The Jabal Akhdar, composed mainly of limestone, rises to over 800 m above sea level and enjoys higher rainfall than any other part of Libya... The vegetation and the general character of the terrain are more reminiscent of Greece and Asia Minor than of Tripolitania or other parts of North Africa.» [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>: 1].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Cyrenaica was originally occupied by a semi-nomadic population conventionally known as Libyan. Contacts between this area and both Mycenaeans and Minoans during the Bronze Age are attested by sporadic though significant discoveries. The region was settled by Greek colonists in and after the late seventh century B.C. 
                        The first settlers were Greeks from the Aegean island of Thera led by a certain Aristoteles, who, after two unsuccessful attempts in the island of Platea off the Libyan coast and in the nearby site of Aziris, settled definitely in the site of Cyrene on the traditional date of 631 B.C. (Herodotus 4.150-158 and <ref target=".././igcyr011000">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>011000</ref>, the well-known inscription bearing the founders' oath). 
                        Aristoteles became king of Cyrene as Battos (Pindarus, <title>Pythia</title> 5.87) and there followed from 631 until c. 440 B.C. a succession of eight kings, alternately named Battos and Arkesilaos, until the assassination of the last, Arkesilaos IV (Herodotus 4.159-205).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The Greeks eventually established four more cities. Euesperides was founded at the end of the seventh century B.C., but received new settlers coming from different cities of Greece in 462 B.C. through the initiative of king Arkesilaos IV of Cyrene. Around 250 B.C. the site was abandoned in favour of the new foundation nearby of Berenice, named after the wife of Ptolemy III Euergetes king of Egypt. Taucheira (or Teucheira) was said to have been founded from Cyrene shortly after 631 B.C. The city received the name Arsinoe, after a queen of Egypt, during the Hellenistic period (between 322 and 220 B.C., not necessarily in 246 B.C., as it was assumed until recently). 
                        The settlement known in the archaic period as the 'port of Barka' was also founded in the seventh century B.C., as the archaeology shows, though Herodotus assigns the founding of Barka (al-Marj) itself to the reign of Arkesilaos II (560-550 B.C.). 
                        The port became a city with name Ptolemais during the Hellenistic period (before 251 B.C. and possibly after 260). At the beginning of the 20th century the Italians founded a new village on the site which became known as Tolemaide, modern Tulmaytha. Apollonia was for many centuries known as the 'port of Cyrene'. The city may have received both its name honouring the patron god of Cyrene and its independence from the mother-city in the second half of the second century B.C.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">After the end of the monarchy at Cyrene, the region saw conflicts between aristocratic and popular parties on the one hand, alliances between different cities and raids by displaced Libyans on the other. At Cyrene itself, the fourth century B.C. was characterized by political struggles. 
                        In 401 B.C. a revolution put a democratic government in place: the reconciliation which followed forced the oligarchs to compromise with their opponents and to set up a mixed constitution (Diodorus 14.34). It is probably to this moderate constitution that the fourth century B.C. decree bearing the ancient oath of the founders (<ref target=".././igcyr011000">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>011000</ref>) belongs. 
                        During the next decades, perhaps in the sixties at the latest, an aggressive reaction by the aristocrats took place, following the intolerable increasing growth in the number of citizens (Aristoteles, <title>Politica</title>, 1319b): a restrictive regime with one thousand citizens was then established [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>]. 
                        As to Euesperides, to cite the most prominent case of a vulnerable situation, the city was attacked by Libyan tribes in 414 B.C. and was saved only by the accidental arrival of the Spartan fleet commanded by Gylippus who was sailing towards Syracuse (Thucydides 7.50).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In 331 B.C., when Alexander the Great, king of Macedon, during his successful Asian expedition, founded Alexandria in Egypt and marched towards the desert oasis of Siwa, the Cyreneans sent an embassy with gifts for the king, namely 300 horses and five four-horses chariots, and were secured against his intervention, becoming his friends and allies (Diodorus 17.49.3; Curtius Rufus 4.7.8).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">After the death of Alexander in 323 B.C, the region was partially conquered by a Spartan adventurer, a former associate of Alexander's treasurer Harpalus, named Thibron. A faction of aristocrats, exiled from Cyrene by the democrats who gained power during the siege imposed by Thibron, sought help from Ptolemy, now in control of Egypt [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>]. He sent an army led by Ophellas. Thibron was defeated, but the Cyreneans lost their freedom: the famous constitutional <foreign>diagramma</foreign> by Ptolemy, acting as an agent of the king of Macedon, was imposed on - and inscribed at - Cyrene (<ref target=".././igcyr010800">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>010800</ref>) in 321 or 320 B.C.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Cyrene and the Greek cities of Cyrenaica were from now on almost continuously in Ptolemaic hands. The cities were actually ruled by a governor installed by Ptolemy and his son and descendant Ptolemy II Philadelphos (Ophellas, 322-308 B.C.; Magas, a stepson of Ptolemy, from 308 or 300 until 258 or 250 B.C.) or by kings of the Ptolemaic dynasty (though they were not always controlled from Alexandria). It is in the third-second centuries B.C. that the Greeks were joined by groups of Greek-speakers of varied origins brought in by the kings of Egypt.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">After the death of Magas, who had at some point taken the royal title at Cyrene and appointed governors for the other cities, some years of struggle followed. Cyrene and the Greek cities of Cyrenaica were again in firm Ptolemaic control in 246 B.C. with the accession of Ptolemy III Euergetes, who married Magas' daughter Berenike. In an inscription found at Adoulis (<title>OGIS</title> I 54) the king contends that he has acquired 'Libya' by inheritance from his father [<bibl><ptr target="#bagnall1976"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It is only in 163 B.C. that Cyrene changed its status. The conflict between the brother kings Ptolemy VI Philometor and Ptolemy VIII Euergetes II led to the agreement of 163 B.C.: while Ptolemy VI was to be the king of Egypt and of the other possessions outside, Cyrene became the kingdom of Ptolemy VIII. One year later Cyrene revolted with the help of the governor left by Ptolemy VIII in charge of the whole Cyrenaica, Ptolemaios Sympetesis (Polybius 31.18.6-7). 
                        The separate status of Cyrene ended in 145 B.C. when Ptolemy VIII became king of Egypt: it remained in his hands until his death in 116 B.C. This king is known, from an inscription found at Cyrene (<ref target=".././igcyr011200">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>011200</ref>), to have bequeathed his kingdom to Rome should he die without an heir. As in fact he left an heir, Cyrenaica still remained in Ptolemaic hands [<bibl><ptr target="#bagnall1976"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">It is not generally agreed though who controlled the region during the last quarter of the second century. Despite the testimony of Iustinus (39.5.2) who writes that Ptolemy VIII left Cyrene to Ptolemy Apion, his son by the concubine Eirene, the epigraphic sources testify that the legitimate son of Ptolemy VIII, Ptolemy IX Soter II, king of Egypt from 116 until 108/7 B.C., remained in control of Cyrenaica until some date between 104 and 101 B.C. According to the literary sources, Ptolemy Apion died in 96 B.C. bequeathing Cyrenaica to Rome. Cyrenaica passed then into Roman control, which, however, was only seriously exercised more than 20 years later.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Alice Bencivenni (rev. Charlotte Roueché)</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="it">L'antica Cirenaica è la regione costiera orientale della Libia. Almeno a partire dal I secolo d.C. era nota anche come Pentapoli, i.e. la federazione di cinque città (Plinius, <title>Naturalis Historia</title>, 5.5.5): da ovest, Euesperides/Berenice (Benghazi), Taucheira/Arsinoe (Tocra, Tukrah), Barka/Ptolemais (Tolemaide, Tulmaytha), Cirene (Shahat), Apollonia (Susa). Queste città furono fondate da coloni greci e non arrivarono mai a controllare completamente il territorio circostante: molti villaggi e piccoli paesi sorsero nell'area lasciando tracce visibili ancora ai nostri giorni.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">«La regione abitata della Cirenaica è caratterizzata per lo più dall'elevato altopiano del Jabal Akhdar (la Montagna Verde) che si spinge verso settentrione fino al Mediterraneo tra il Golfo della Sirte (la Gran Sirte) a ovest e le basse, aride terre costiere della Marmarica verso Alessandria. L'altopiano si eleva in due livelli, e mentre a ovest c'è un'ampia striscia costiera tra i piedi del Jabal e Benghazi, questa si restringe progressivamente in direzione nord-est e scompare quasi completamente dopo Ptolemais. Verso est il territorio si inclina più gradualmente e, poiché diventa più arido, gli insediamenti sono più radi verso Tubruq. ... Il Jabal Akhdar, composto per lo più da pietra calcarea, si eleva a più di 800 m s.l.m. e gode di piogge abbondanti più che ogni altra parte delle Libia... La vegetazione e il carattere generale del terreno ricordano più la Grecia e l'Asia Minore che la Tripolitania o altre parti del Nord Africa.» [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>: 1; trad. AB].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">La Cirenaica fu originariamente occupata da una popolazione seminomade convenzionalmente nota come 'libica'. Contatti tra questa area e genti micenee e minoiche durante l'età del Bronzo sono attestate da scoperte sporadiche ma significative. La regione fu occupata da coloni greci a partire dal tardo VII secolo a.C. 
                        I primi colonizzatori erano Greci provenienti dall'isola egea di Tera guidati da un certo Aristoteles che, dopo due infruttuosi tentativi nell'isola di Platea al largo della costa libica e nel vicino sito di Aziris, si stabilì definitivamente nel sito di Cirene, secondo la tradizione nel 631 a.C. (Herodotus 4.150-158 e <ref target=".././igcyr011000">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>011000</ref>, la ben nota iscrizione con il giuramento dei fondatori). Aristoteles diventò re di Cirene con il nome di Battos (Pindarus, <title>Pythia</title> 5.87) e tra il 631 e il 440 a.C. si successero otto re, alternativamente chiamati Battos e Arkesilaos, fino all'uccisione dell'ultimo, Arkesilaos IV (Herodotus 4.159-205).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">I Greci fondarono nel corso del tempo altre quattro città. Euesperides fu fondata alla fine del VII secolo a.C., ma ricevette nuovi coloni provenienti da diverse città della Grecia nel 462 a.C. per iniziativa del re Arkesilaos IV di Cirene. Intorno al 250 a.C. il sito fu abbandonato a vantaggio della vicina nuova fondazione di Berenice, dal nome della moglie di Tolemeo III Euergetes re d'Egitto.
                        Taucheira (o Teucheira) era nota per essere stata fondata da Cirene poco dopo il 631 a.C. La città ricevette il nome di Arsinoe, una delle regine d'Egitto con questo nome, durante l'età ellenistica (tra il 322 e il 220 a.C., non necessariamente nel 246 a.C., come si è ritenuto fino a poco tempo fa). Anche l'insediamento noto in epoca arcaica come il 'porto di Barka' fu fondato nel VII secolo a.C., come è attestato dai ritrovamenti archeologici, benché Erodoto assegni la fondazione della stessa Barka (al-Marj) al regno di Arkesilaos II (560-550 B.C.). 
                       Il porto divenne una città di nome Ptolemais durante l'età ellenistica, prima del 251 e forse solo dopo il 260. All'inizio del XX secolo gli Italiani fondarono sul sito un nuovo villaggio che divenne noto come Tolemaide, oggi Tulmaytha. Apollonia fu nota per molti secoli come il 'porto di Cirene'. La città può aver ricevuto il suo nome in onore della divinità patrona di Cirene e la sua indipendenza dalla madrepatria nella seconda metà del II secolo a.C.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Dopo la fine della monarchia a Cirene, nella regione ebbero luogo conflitti tra fazioni aristocratiche e popolari da una parte, alleanze tra città diverse e incursioni di Libici dall'altra. Per quel che concerne Cirene, il IV secolo a.C. fu caratterizzato da conflitti politici. 
                        Nel 401 a.C. si instaurò con la violenza un regime di tipo democratico: la riconciliazione che ne seguì costrinse gli oligarchici ad un compromesso con i loro oppositori nella forma di una costituzione mista (Diodorus 14.34). Con ogni probabilità è a questa costituzione che appartiene la promulgazione del decreto del IV secolo a.C. che contiene e conserva l'antico giuramento dei fondatori della città (<ref target=".././igcyr011000">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>011000</ref>). 
                        Durante i decenni successivi, forse negli anni sessanta al più tardi, si verificò la dura reazione degli oligarchici, ormai intolleranti di fronte al continuo ampliamento del corpo civico (Aristoteles, <title>Politica</title>, 1319b): un regime fortemente restrittivo con un corpo civico di mille unità fu allora instaurato [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>]. Per quel che riguarda Euesperides, per citare il caso più rappresentativo della vulnerabilità degli insediamenti greci della Cirenaica, la città fu attaccata da tribù libiche nel 414 a.C. e fu salvata solo grazie all'arrivo fortuito della flotta spartana comandata da Gilippo e diretta a Siracusa (Thucydides 7.50).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Nel 331 a.C., quando Alessandro il Grande re di Macedonia, nel corso della sua fortunata spedizione in Asia, fondò Alessandria in Egitto e marciò verso l'oasi di Siwa, i Cirenei inviarono una ambasceria con doni per il re (300 cavalli e cinque quadrighe) e furono così risparmiati dal suo intervento diventando suoi amici e alleati (Diodorus 17.49.3; Curtius Rufus 4.7.8).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Dopo la morte di Alessandro nel 323 a.C., la regione fu parzialmente conquistata da un avventuriero spartano, già compagno di Arpalo il tesoriere di Alessandro, di nome Thibron. Una fazione di aristocratici, esiliati da Cirene dai democratici che avevano conquistato il potere nel corso dell'assedio imposto da Thibron, cercarono rifugio e aiuto presso Tolemeo, allora a capo dell'Egitto [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>].  Quest'ultimo inviò un esercito guidato da Ophellas. Thibron fu sconfitto, ma i Cirenei persero la loro libertà: il famoso <foreign>diagramma</foreign> costituzionale di Tolemeo, che agiva in veste di agente del re di Macedonia, fu imposto - e iscritto - a Cirene (<ref target=".././igcyr010800">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>010800</ref>) nel 321 o nel 320 a.C.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Cirene e le città greche della Cirenaica furono da quest'epoca in avanti quasi ininterrottamente nelle mani dei Tolemei. Le città erano in effetti controllate da un governatore insediato da Tolemeo e poi dal suo figlio e successore Tolemeo II Philadelphos (Ophellas, 322-308 a.C.; Magas, un figliastro di Tolemeo, dal 308 o dal 300 fino al 258 o al 250 a.C.) o da re della dinastia tolemaica (sebbene esse non fossero sempre controllate da Alessandria). E' nei secoli terzo e secondo a.C. che i Greci furono raggiunti da genti parlanti greco di varia origine portati dai re d'Egitto.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Dopo la morte di Magas, che ad un certo punto aveva preso il titolo regio a Cirene e aveva designato governatori per le altre città, si produssero conflitti che durarono alcuni anni. Cirene e le città greche di Cirenaica furono di nuovo sotto il saldo controllo dei Tolemei nel 246 a.C. con l'ascesa al trono di Tolemeo III Euergetes, che sposò Berenice, la figlia di Magas. Nella iscrizione rinvenuta ad Adoulis OGIS I 54 il re dichiara di aver acquisito la 'Libia' per via ereditaria dal padre [<bibl><ptr target="#bagnall1976"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Solo nel 163 a.C. Cirene cambiò il suo status. Il conflitto tra i re fratelli Tolemeo VI Philometor e Tolemeo VIII Euergetes II portò all'accordo del 163 a.C.: mentre Tolemeo VI doveva essere re d'Egitto e degli altri possedimenti esterni, Cirene diventava il regno di Tolemeo VIII. 
                        Un anno più tardi Cirene si ribellò con l'aiuto del governatore a capo dell'intera Cirenaica designato da Tolemeo VIII, Ptolemaios Sympetesis (Polybius 31.18.6-7). La separazione di Cirene finì nel 145 a.C. quando Tolemeo VIII divenne re d'Egitto: rimase infatti nelle sue mani fino alla sua morte nel 116 a.C. Si sa da una iscrizione rinvenuta a Cirene (<ref target=".././igcyr011200">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>011200</ref>) che il re aveva deciso di lasciare il suo regno a Roma se fosse morto senza eredi. Dato che in effetti lasciò un erede, la Cirenaica rimase ancora in mano tolemaica [<bibl><ptr target="#bagnall1976"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Non c'è accordo tra gli studiosi su chi abbia controllato la regione nell'ultimo quarto del secondo secolo a.C. Nonostante la testimonianza di Giustino (39.5.2) che scrive che Tolemeo VIII lasciò Cirene a Tolemeo Apione, figlio della sua concubina Eirene, le fonti epigrafiche attestano che il figlio legittimo di Tolemeo VIII, Tolemeo IX Soter II, re d'Egitto dal 116 al 108/7 a.C., controllò la Cirenaica fino ad un periodo compreso tra il 104 e il 101 a.C. Secondo le fonti letterarie, Tolemeo Apione morì nel 96 a.C., lasciando la Cirenaica a Roma. La Cirenaica passò allora sotto il potere dei Romani, potere esercitato seriamente solo dopo più di 20 anni.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Alice Bencivenni</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="fr">La Cyrénaïque antique est la région côtière orientale de la Libye. Au moins à partir du I<hi rend="superscript">er</hi> siècle après J.-C., elle était connue aussi comme la Pentapole, une fédération de cinq cités (Plinius, <title>Naturalis Historia</title>, 5.5.5), à savoir d'Ouest en Est: Euhespérides/Bérénikè (Benghazi), Taucheira/Arsinoè (Tocra, Tukrah), Barka/Ptolemaïs (Tolemaide, Tulmaytha), Cyrène (Shahat), Apollonia (Susa). Ces cités furent fondées par des colons grecs, qui ne parvinrent jamais à contrôler complètement l'arrière-pays: de nombreux villages et de petits établissements se dressaient à l'intérieur, laissant encore aujourd'hui des traces visibles.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">"La région où est implantée la Cyrénaïque est caractérisée par le plateau supérieur du Djebel Akhdar (la Montagne Verte) qui se projette vers le Nord en direction de la Méditerranée entre le Golfe de Sidra (la Grande Syrte) à l'Ouest et la zone côtière basse et aride de la Marmarique en direction d'Alexandrie. Le plateau s'élève en deux emmarchements et, tandis qu'à l'Ouest la bande côtière est large entre le pied du djebel et Benghazi, celle-ci se rétrécit progressivement en direction du Nord-Est, au point de disparaître presque complètement au-delà de Ptolémaïs. Encore plus loin à l'Est, le niveau descend plus graduellement et, comme la sécheresse augmente, les implantations sont plus disséminées vers Tobrouk (...). Le Djebel Akhdar, composé principalement de calcaire, s'élève à plus de 800 m. d'altitude et bénéficie de plus de précipitations que toute autre contrée de la Libye (...). La végétation et les caractéristiques du terrain rappellent davantage la Grèce ou l'Asie mineure que la Tripolitaine ou d'autres régions d'Afrique du Nord" [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>: 1; trad. CDL].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">La Cyrénaïque fut occupée à l'origine par une population semi-nomade conventionnellement appelée "libyenne". Des contacts entre cette région et les Mycéniens et Minoens pendant l'âge du bronze sont attestés par des découvertes sporadiques, mais significatives. La région fut occupée par des colons grecs à partir de la fin du VII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle av. J.-C. Les premiers colons étaient des Grecs provenant de l'île égéenne de Théra, guidés par un certain Aristotélès qui, après deux tentatives manquées sur l'îlot de Platée au large de la côte libyenne et sur le site voisin d'Aziris, s'établirent définitivement sur le site de Cyrène en 631, selon la tradition (Hérodote 4.150-158 et <ref target=".././igcyr011000">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>011000</ref>, la célèbre inscription portant le serment des fondateurs). Aristotélès devint roi de Cyrène sous le nom de Battos (Pindare, <title>Pyth</title>. 5.87) et de 631 à 440 av.J.-C. se succédèrent huit rois nommés alternativement Battos et Arcésilas, jusqu'à l'assassinat du dernier, Arcésilas IV (Hérodote 4.159-205).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Les Grecs fondèrent au cours du temps quatre autres cités. Euhespérides fut fondée à la fin du VII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle av. J.-C., mais reçut de nouveaux colons provenant de diverses cités de Grèce en 462 à l'initiative du roi de Cyrène Arcésilas IV. Vers 250 av. J.-C., le site fut abandonné au profit de la nouvelle fondation voisine de Bérénikè, du nom de l'épouse de Ptolémée III Evergète, roi d'Égypte. Taucheira (ou Teucheira) est réputée avoir été fondée par Cyrène peu après 631 av. J.-C. 
                        La cité reçut le nom d'Arsinoè, une des reines d'Égypte, durant la période hellénistique (entre 322 et 220 av. J.-C., mais pas nécessairement en 246, comme on l'a pensé longtemps). L'établissement connu à l'époque archaïque comme le "port de Barka" fut fondé lui aussi au VII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle, comme le prouvent les découvertes archéologiques, bien qu'Hérodote attribue la fondation de Barka elle-même (el-Marj) au règne d'Arcésilas II (560-550). 
                        Le port devint une cité nommée Ptolémaïs à l'époque hellénistique, avant 251 et peut-être seulement après 260. Au début du XX<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle, les Italiens fondèrent sur le site un nouveau village connu sous le nom de Tolemaide, aujourd'hui Tulmaytah. Apollonia fut pendant plusieurs siècles seulement le "port de Cyrène". La cité, qui doit son nom au dieu patron de Cyrène, a dû devenir indépendante de la cité-mère dans la seconde moitié du II<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle av. J.-C.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Après la fin de la monarchie à Cyrène, la région fut le théâtre de conflits entre factions aristocratiques et populaires d'une part, d'alliances changeantes entre cités et d'incursions libyennes d'autre part. En ce qui concerne Cyrène, le IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle fut marqué par des conflits politiques. En 401 fut instauré par la force un régime de type démocratique; la réconciliation qui s'ensuivit contraignit les oligarques à un compromis avec leurs opposants sous la forme d'une constitution mixte (Diodore, 14.34). 
                        Selon toute probabilité, c'est à ce régime que l'on doit la promulgation du décret du IV<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle qui reproduit l'antique serment des fondateurs de la cité (<ref target=".././igcyr011000">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>011000</ref>). Pendant les décennies suivantes, probablement vers 360 au plus tard, se produisit une sévère réaction des oligarques devant l'augmentation continue du corps civique (Aristote, <title>Politique</title>, 1319b): un régime très restrictif avec un corps civique des Mille fut alors instauré [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>]. 
                        En ce qui concerne Euhespérides, pour citer le cas le plus représentatif de la vulnérabilité des établissements grecs de Cyrénaïque, la cité fut attaquée par des tribus libyennes en 414 et ne dut son salut qu'à l'arrivée fortuite de la flotte spartiate commandée par Gylippe, en provenance de Syracuse (Thucydide, 7.50).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">En 331, lorsqu'Alexandre le Grand, roi de Macédoine, au cours de sa brillante expédition en Asie, fonda Alexandrie d'Égypte puis se dirigea vers l'oasis de Siwa, les Cyrénéens envoyèrent une ambassade pour offrir au roi trois cents chevaux et cinq quadriges et s'épargnèrent ainsi une intervention en devenant ses amis et alliés (Diodore, 17.49.3; Quinte-Curce, 4.7.8).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Après la mort d'Alexandre en 323, la région fut partiellement conquise par l'aventurier spartiate Thibron, ancien compagnon d'Harpale, le trésorier d'Alexandre. Une faction d'aristocrates, exilés de Cyrène par les démocrates qui avaient pris le pouvoir pendant que Thibron assiégeait la cité, cherchèrent refuge et aide auprès de Ptolémée, alors maître de l'Égypte [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>]. 
                        Ce dernier envoya une armée dirigée par Ophellas. Thibron fut battu, mais les Cyrénéens y perdirent leur liberté: les dispositions constitutionnelles du fameux diagramma de Ptolémée, qui agissait comme représentant du roi de Macédoine, furent imposées - et gravées - à Cyrène (<ref target=".././igcyr010800">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>010800</ref>) en 321 ou 320 av. J.-C.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Cyrène et les cités grecques de Cyrénaïque furent à partir de ce moment aux mains des Ptolémées de façon presque ininterrompue. Dans la pratique, les cités furent contrôlées par un gouverneur nommé par Ptolémée, puis par son fils et successeur Ptolémée II Philadelphe (Ophellas de 322 à 308; Magas, beau-fils de Ptolémée de 308 ou 300 jusqu'à 258 ou 250 av. J.-C.) ou par d'autres rois de la dynastie ptolémaïque (même si ces gouverneurs ne dépendaient pas toujours d'Alexandrie). C'est au cours des III<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> et II<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècles que les Grecs se virent adjoindre des populations hellénophones d'origines diverses, installées là par les rois d'Égypte.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Après la mort de Magas, qui à un certain moment avait pris le titre de roi de Cyrène et avait nommé des gouverneurs dans les autres cités, se produisirent des conflits d'une certaine durée. Cyrène et les cités grecques de Cyrénaïque furent à nouveau sous le contrôle étroit des Ptolémées en 246, avec l'accession au trône de Ptolémée III Evergète, qui épousa Bérénice, la fille de Magas. Dans l'inscription d'Adoulis <title>OGIS</title> I.54, le roi déclare avoir acquis la "Libye" par héritage de son père [<bibl><ptr target="#bagnall1976"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Ce n'est qu'en 163 av. J.-C. que Cyrène changea de statut. Le conflit entre les frères royaux Ptolémée VI Philometor et Ptolémée VIII Evergète II aboutit à l'accord de 163 av. J.-C.: tandis que Ptolémée VI devait être roi d'Égypte et des autres possessions extérieures, Cyrène devenait le royaume de Ptolémée VIII. Une année plus tard, Cyrène se révolta avec l'aide du gouverneur chargé par Ptolémée VIII de la Cyrénaïque entière, Ptolémée Sympetesis (Polybe 31.18.6-7). La défection de Cyrène prit fin en 145, quand Ptolémée VIII devint roi d'Égypte: elle resta en son pouvoir jusqu'à sa mort en 116. On sait par une inscription retrouvée à Cyrène (<ref target=".././igcyr011200">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>011200</ref>) que le roi avait décidé de léguer son royaume à Rome s'il devait mourir sans héritier. Mais de fait, comme il eut un héritier, la Cyrénaïque resta encore sous la domination ptolémaïque [<bibl><ptr target="#bagnall1976"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">L'accord n'est pas fait sur l'identité du souverain qui régna sur la région dans le dernier quart du second siècle av. J.-C. En dépit du témoignage de Justin (39.5.2), qui écrit que Ptolémée VIII légua Cyrène à Ptolémée Apion, fils de sa concubine Eirènè, les sources épigraphiques attestent que le fils légitime de Ptolémée VIII, Ptolémée IX Sôter II, roi d'Égypte de 116 à 108/7, exerça son contrôle sur la Cyrénaïque jusqu'à une date comprise entre 104 et 101. Selon les sources littéraires, Ptolémée Apion mourut en 96 av. J.-C., laissant la Cyrénaïque à Rome. La Cyrénaïque passa alors sous le pouvoir des Romains, pouvoir exercé pleinement après un délai de plus de vingt ans.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Alice Bencivenni (trad. Catherine Dobias-Lalou)</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="ar">كيرينايكي الإغريقية (كيرينايكي في العصر الإغريقي)
كيرينايكي القديمة هي المنطقة الساحلية الشرقية من ليبيا،  وكانت تعرف أيضا بالبنتابولس Pentapolis  (بمعنى اتحاد المدن الخمس) على الأقل من القرن الأول الميلادي وفق ما أشار إليه بليني Pliny, Naturalis Historia 5.5.5.)): وهن من الغرب إلى الشرق، يوسبريدس/برنيكي (بنغازي) و تاوخيرا/أرسينوي (توكرة) و باركي/ بطوليمايس (طلميثة) وكيريني (شحات) بالإضافة إلى أبولونيا (سوسة). وقد أُسست هذه المدن من قبل المستعمرين الإغريق الذين لم يسيطروا بشكل كامل على أريافها. ويمكن الآن رؤية أطلال العديد من القرى والبلدات الصغيرة التي كانت قد نمت في هذه المناطق المحيطة.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">« اتصف عموم الجزء المستوطن من إقليم كيرينايكي بهضبة مرتفعة تسمى الجبل الأخضر، حيث تبرز شمالاً نحو البحر الأبيض المتوسط وتمتد ​​بين خليج السدرة (سرت الكبرى) إلى الغرب والأراضي الساحلية المنخفضة الجافة لإقليم مارماريكا باتجاه الإسكندرية. ترتفع هذه الهضبة إلى درجتين، فبينما يكون الشريط الساحلي في الغرب فسيحاً بين سفح الجبل وبنغازي فإنه يضيق تدريجيا كلما اتجه إلى الشمال الشرقي ويختفي بشكل شبه كلي بعد طليمثة. أما باتجاه الشرق، فالأرض تنخفض بشكل تدريجي وتصبح أكثر جفافاً، لذلك فإن الاستيطان نواحي طبرق يكون ضَئِيلاً... ويتكون الجبل الأخضر بشكل أساسي من الحجر الجيري، ويرتفع إلى أكثر من 800 متر فوق مستوى سطح البحر، ويتمتع  بأعلى نسبة من الأمطار أكثر من أي جزء آخر من ليبيا ... والغطاء النباتي والطابع العام لسطح لأرض لكيرينايكي يشبه إلى حد كبير تلك التي في بلاد اليونان وآسيا الصغرى أكثر منه في إقليم طرابلس أو أجزاء أخرى من شمال أفريقيا [Kenrick 2013: 1].</p>
                      <p xml:lang="ar"> كانت كيرينايكي مأهولة في الأصل من قبل سكان شبه رحل معروفين تقليدياً بالليبين، وقد دلت الاكتشافات الهامة رغم ندرتها  على وجود اتصالات بين سكان هذه المنطقة وكل من الميكينيين والمينويين خلال العصر البرونزي، وخلال أواخر القرن السابع قبل الميلاد وما بعده استوطن المستعمرون الإغريق هذا الإقليم، وقد جاء المستوطنين الأوائل الإغريق من ثيرا احدى جزربحر إيجا، وقد قادهم شخص يدعى أريستوتيليس، واستقر هؤلاء بشكل نهائي، بعد محاولتين غير ناجحتين في جزيرة بلاتيا Platea  قبالة السواحل الليبية وفي موقع أزيريس Aziris، في موقع كيريني عند التاريخ المتعارف عليه 631 قبل الميلاد (Herodotus 4.150-158) ورابط إلى ([IGCyr² 011000]  (النقش المعروف باسم قسم المؤسسين (. أصبح أريستوتيليس ملك كيريني حيث عرف باسم باتوس (Pindarus, Pythia 5.87) ، ثم تبعته سلسلة من ثمانية ملوك في الفترة من 631 حتى 440 ق. م، أُطلق عليهم بالتناوب اسمي باتوس وأركيسلاوس، حتى تم اغتيال آخرهم وهو أركيسلاوس الرابع (205 (Herodotus 4.159).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">أنشأ الإغريق في نهاية المطاف أربع مدن أخرى، حيث أُسست يوسبريدس في نهاية القرن السابع ق. م.، بيد أنها اسُتوطنت من قبل قادمين جدد من مدن مختلفة من بلاد الإغريق عام 462 ق.م. بناءاً على مبادرة من ملك كيريني أركيسلاوس الرابع. وفي حوالي 250 ق. م هُجر هذا الموقع واستعيظ عنه بمكان جديد في الجوار سُمي ’برنيكي‘، الذي أخذ اسم زوجة ملك مصر بطليموس الثالث (يورجيتس). أما مدينة تاوخيرا (توكره)، فيُقال أن كيريني كانت قد أسستها بعد بفترة وجيزة من 631 ق. م. وأخذت اسم ملكة مصر ’أرسينوي‘ خلال الفترة الهلنستية (بين 322 و 220 ق. م.، وليس بالضرورة في عام 246 ق م، كما افتُرض حتى وقت قريب). كما بينت الآثار أن المستوطنة المعروفة في العصر الآرخي كميناء لباركي تأسست أيضا في القرن السابع ق. م. رغم أن هيرودوت نسب تأسيس باركي (المرج) نفسها إلى عهد أركيسلاوس الثاني (560- 550 ق. م.)، وأصبح الميناء مدينة باسم بطوليمايس خلال الفترة الهلنستية (قبل 251 ق.م وربما بعد 260 ق.م.)
وفي بداية القرن العشرين، أسس الايطاليون قرية جديدة في هذا الموقع التي عرفت باسم Tolemaide، وهي طلميثة الحديثة. أما أبولونيا فقد عُرفت لقرون عديدية كميناء لمدينة كيريني، و ربما مُنحت هذه المدينة اسم أبولونيا تكريما للمؤله [أبوللو] راعي مدينة كيريني و بمناسبة استقلالها عن المدينة الأم في النصف الثاني من القرن الثاني ق. م.</p>
                  
  <p xml:lang="ar">شهد الإقليم بعد نهاية الحكم الملكي في مدينة كيريني صراعاً بين الأحزاب الأرستقراطية والديمقراطية من جهة، والتحالفات بين مدن مختلفة وغارات الليبيين الرحل من جهة أخرى، وقد تميزالوضع في مدينة كيريني نفسها بالصراعات السياسية. وفي عام 401  ق. م. استلمت حكومة ديمقراطية زمام الأمور بعد ثورة شهدتها المدينة: المصالحة التي تلت ذلك أجبرت القلة الأرستقراطية على قبول تسوية مع خصومهم ووضع دستور مشترك (Diodorus 14.34). ومن المحتمل أن يكون هذا الدستور المعتدل هو المرسوم الذي يمثل قسم المؤسسين القديم الذي ينتمي للقرن الرابع ق. م. الربط إلى (IGCyr² 011000). و خلال العقود التالية، وربما في الستينيات على أبعد تقدير، حدثت رَدَّةُ فِعْل عنيفة من قبل الأرستقراطيين في أعقاب النمو السكاني المتزايد الذي لم يعد يُحتمل (Aristoteles, Politica, 1319b)، لذلك أُنْشِئَ نظاماً مشدداً مكوناً من ألف مواطن [[Laronde 1987. بالنسبة ليوسبريدس، فهي تمثل الحالة الأكثر جلاءاً لموقف الضعف، حيث هُوجمت المدينة من قبل القبائل الليبية  في عام 414  ق. م.، ولكن تم أنقذها بواسطة الأسطول الإسبرطي بقيادة قيليبوس (Gylippus) الذي وصل صدفةً إلى المدينة بينما كان مبحراً نحو سيراكيوز (Thucydides 7.50)..
في عام 331 ق. م. عندما أسس الإسكندر الأكبر ملك مقدونيا الإسكندرية في مصر- خلال الحملة الآسيوية الناجحة- ثم سار نحو واحة سيوه الصحراوية، أرسل له الكيرينيون سفراء مع هدايا متمثلة في 300 حصاناً وخمس من العربات التي تجرها أربعة أحصنة، ليضمنوا عدم تدخله في شوؤنهم، وليصبحوا أصدقاءاً وحلفاءاً له(Diodorus 17.49.3; Curtius Rufus 4.7.8)</p>

                    <p xml:lang="ar">إثر وفاة الإسكندر عام 323 ق. م اُحتُل الإقليم جزئيا من قبل مغامر إسبرطي- كان في السابق مقرباً لأرابالوس صديق الإسكندر- يسُمي ثيبرون، لكن فِئَة من الأرستقراطيين، الذين نفاهم الديمقراطيين من كيريني عندما وصلوا الى السلطة، طلبوا المساعدة من بطليموس، حاكم مصر، أثناء حصار ثيبرون للمدينة [Laronde 1987]. بعث بطليموس جيشاً بقيادة أوفيلاس، فهزم ثيبرون ، لكن الكيرينيين خسروا حريتهم، فقد صدر في كيريني دستور بطليموس الشهير بتاريخ 321 أو 320 ق. م.، بالنيابة عن للملك المقدوني وكان مفروضا على كيريني (رابط إلى  IGCyr² 010900]).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">منذ الآن صارت كيريني والمدن الإغريقية الأخرى في كيرينايكي تقريباً وبشكل مستمرمن هذا التاريخ فصاعدا في أيدي البطالمة، وكانت هذه المدن تُحكم في الواقع  من قبل حاكم يُعين من قبل بطليموس وابنه وسلالة بطليموس الثاني فيلادلفوس (أوفيلاس 322- 308 ق. م وماجاس ربيب بطليموس من 308 أو 300 حتى 258 أو 250 ق. م)، أو تحكم بواسطة ملوك من الأسرة الملكية البطلمية ،على الرغم من أنهم لم يحكموا دائما من الإسكندرية بشكل مباشر. وعَمل ملوك مصر الإغريق في القرنين الثالث والثاني ق. م. على أدخال مجموعات من الناطقين باللغة الإغريقية من أصول متنوعة إلى إقليم كيرينايكي.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">تبعت وفاة ماجاس - الذي لأسباب ما أخذ اللقب الملكي في كيريني وعين حكاماً لغيرها من المدن- بضع سنوات من الصراع، ثم عادت كيريني والمدن الإغريقية الكيرينايكية الأخرى مرةً ثانيةً إلى حضيرة  الدولة البطلمية مع اعتلاء بطليموس الثالث (يورجيتس) الحكم في مصر في عام 246 ق.م. الذي تزوج برنيكي ابنة ماجاس، ويُبين نقش وجد في عدوليس (Adoulis) (OGIS I 54)  أن هذا الملك يؤكد أنه حصل علي ليبيا عن طريق الوراثة من والده [<bibl><ptr target="#bagnall1976"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">لم يتغير وضع كيريني إلا في عام 163 ق.م.، فقد نتج عن الصراع بين الملوك الأشقاء بطليموس السادس (فيلوماتر) وبطليموس الثامن (يورجيتس الثاني) اتفاق في سنة 163 ق.م. الذي بموجبه يكون لبطليموس السادس مُلك مصر وممتلكات أخرى في الخارج، و تكون كيرني مملكةً لبطليموس الثامن. وبعد عام واحد ثارت كيريني بمساعدة بطليموس سيمبيتيسيس وهوالحاكم المُعين من قبل بطليموس الثامن لكل إقليم كيرينايكي (Polybius 31.18.6-7). وفي سنة 145 ق.م. عندما أصبح بطليموس الثامن ملكاً لمصر وبذلك انتهى وضع كيريني المنفصل واستمرت تحت سيطرته حتى وافته المنية عام 116 ق.م.، ويُعرف من نقش وجد في مدينة كيريني أن هذا الملك  كان قد أوصى بمملكته إلى روما في حال مات ولم يكن له وريث (SEG 9.7)، وبما أنه في واقع الأمر قد ترك من يخلفه  فقد ظلت كيرينايكي في أيدي البطالمة  [<bibl><ptr target="#bagnall1976"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">عموماً ليس هناك اتفاق حول مَنْ سيطر على الإقليم  خلال الربع الأخير من القرن الثاني ق.م.، فعلى الرغم من شهادة جوستين (Iustinus 39.5.2) الذي كتب أن بطليموس الثامن ترك كيريني لبطليموس أبيون- ابنه من محظيتة إيريني        - تشهد المصادر الكتابية (النقوش) أن الابن الشرعي لبطليموس الثامن هو بطليموس التاسع (سوتر الثاني)، ملك مصر من عام 116 حتى 108/7 ق.م.، ظل يسيطر على كيريني حتى فترة ما بين السنوات 104 و 101 ق.م. ووفقاً للمصادر الأدبية، توفي بطليموس أبيون في 96 ق.م مُوصياً بكيرينايكي لروما، وإثر ذلك آل الإقليم إلى السيطرة الرومانية، ومع ذلك، لم يبدأ حكمهم الفعلي إلا بعد مرور أكثر من 20 عامًا. 
(إعداد: أليس بينسيفيني. مراجعة: شارلوت روشي. ترجمة: منى عبدالحميد).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">Alice Bencivenni (rev. Charlotte Roueché; translated by Muna Abdelhamed)</p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div xml:id="scholarship">
                    <head>
                        <seg xml:lang="en">Scholarship</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="it">Storia degli studi</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="fr">Historique des recherches</seg>
                        <seg xml:lang="ar">الدراسات</seg>
                    </head>
                    <p xml:lang="en">European travellers and scholars began visiting Cyrenaica already in the 18th century, although the area was difficult to access since its incorporation in the Ottoman empire in the 16th century. These first travellers were interested in copying inscriptions as well as - or, often, more than - in recognizing ancient ruins [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>: 18].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The French consul in Tripoli, Claude Le Maire, visited Cyrene in 1706, briefly reported about it and copied the first inscription, <ref target="https://ircyr2020.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/en/inscriptions/C.316.html"><title>IRCyr2020</title> C.316</ref> [Le Maire in <bibl><ptr target="#lucas1712"/></bibl>; cf. <bibl><ptr target="#omont1902"/></bibl>]. Granger, pseudonym of Félix Tourtachot, a French surgeon, went to Cyrene in the thirties of the 18th century and probably copied there three inscriptions that were later attached to the papers of Michel Fourmont, professor at the Collège de France [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>: 18-19]. 
                        In 1817 the Italian physician Paolo Della Cella was the first traveller who extensively visited the antiquities of Cyrenaica, describing in particular Cyrene and Apollonia [<bibl><ptr target="#dellacella1819"/></bibl>]. A man with a good classical education, he was able to copy Greek and Latin inscriptions. Father Pacifico from Monte Cassiano visited the Pentapolis in 1819 leaving a brief description of it [published in <bibl><ptr target="#delaporte1825"/></bibl>] and some copies of inscriptions. Subsequently, the French painter Jean-Raimond Pacho visited Cyrenaica in 1824-1825 and the detailed account of his voyage, published after his death, provides copies of a great number of inscriptions from Cyrene, Taucheira and Barka [<bibl><ptr target="#pacho1827"/></bibl>]. 
                        These works, together with some copies by the Danish count J.C. Graber de Hemsö, consul at Tripoli, and some others, probably those by Father Pacifico, handed over to Pietro Negri, the consul of Sardinia in Tripoli, were the principal sources for the edition of the Greek inscriptions from Cyrenaica included by Johannes Franz and August Boeckh in the third volume of the <title>Corpus Inscriptionum Graecarum</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#CIG"/></bibl>) [Berlin 1853: pars XXXI nos. 5129-5362b].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">An expedition sponsored by the British Admiralty in 1822 and led by the brothers Frederick and H. George Beechey had, as a principal outcome, the drawing of two important maps of Cyrene [<bibl><ptr target="#beechey1828"/></bibl>: 404-405; 430-431]. As a consequence of this voyage, the British vice-consul in Tripoli W. Warrington sent two expeditions in 1826 and in 1827 led by his sons Frederick and H. George Warrington with the declared purpose of collecting antiquities: five boxes, including one inscription, arrived in England as a result [<bibl><ptr target="#luni1998"/></bibl>: 336]. The French vice-consul in Tripoli and then in Benghazi Jean Vattier de Bourville was entrusted with a mission by his government and in 1847-1848 observed some inscriptions during his excavations at Benghazi, Cyrene and Ptolemais (where from the fortress wall he removed the inscription of the Byzantine Emperor Anastasius now in the Louvre): these inscriptions, reported by A.-J. Letronne [<bibl><ptr target="#letronne1828"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#letronne1848"/></bibl>] and republished by Vattier de Bourville [<bibl><ptr target="#vattier1850"/></bibl>], were included in the <foreign>Addenda</foreign> of the fourth volume of (<bibl><ptr target="#CIG"/></bibl>) [Berlin 1859].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The first 'scientific' expedition to excavate in Cyrenaica was the one led by R. Murdoch Smith and Edwin A. Porcher in 1860-1861 [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>]. They began excavating in Cyrene at their own expense, but they were later funded by the British government: about thirty new texts were discovered on that occasion.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">These new Greek inscriptions were included in two important epigraphic collections which made them known to a wider public: in 1905, the <title>Sammlung der griechischen Dialekt-Inschriften</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#SGDI"/></bibl>), by Hermann Collitz and Friedrich Bechtel (III.2, 4833-4870) and in 1923, the <title>Dialectorum graecarum exempla epigraphica potiora</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#DGE"/></bibl>), by Eduard Schwyzer.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The next authorized expedition to Cyrene was led by the Americans with Richard Norton in 1910-1911: the epigraphist of the team, Herbert de Cou, was shot dead for unknown reasons on the excavation (March 11, 1911). The promising work of the group is attested by the <title>Inscriptions from the Cyrenaica</title> published in 1913 by D.M. Robinson in the <title>American Journal of Archaeology</title> [17, <bibl><ptr target="#robinson1913"/></bibl>: 157-200; cf. 193-200 for the corrections of (<bibl><ptr target="#CIG"/></bibl>) following the notes by H. de Cou].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In the same year, 1910, the Italian archaeologist Federico Halbherr had led an expedition to Libya with the support of the Italian Government and the consent of the Turks: Gaetano De Sanctis was in the team. Many drawings of inscriptions by Halbherr are to be found in his archive kept at the Accademia Roveretana degli Agiati [<bibl><ptr target="#paci1991"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">After their invasion of Libya in 1911, the Italians started to investigate the antiquities of Cyrenaica systematically, excavating mainly in Cyrene, but also at Ptolemais and Apollonia, from 1912 until 1942. In 1912 a Soprintendenza per le Antichità della Cirenaica was established in the region and from 1925 onwards an Extraordinary Mission worked every summer. Although connected with a military occupation that led to inescapable episodes disrespectful towards the preservation of the archaeological remains, these regular excavations made a fundamental contribution to the knowledge of the sites and their epigraphy.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">A lot of important publications appeared during this period in the <title>Notiziario Archeologico</title> (1915-1927) and in the series of the <title>Africa Italiana</title> (1927-1941). Already in 1925 Silvio Ferri published some major texts such as the diagramma by Ptolemy (<ref target=".././igcyr010800">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>010800</ref>) and in 1928 a special issue of the <title>Rivista di Filologia e di Istruzione Classica</title> was wholly dedicated to the inscriptions from Cyrene. In 1932-1936 the two fundamental volumes <title>Documenti antichi dell'Africa italiana</title> by Gaspare Oliverio were published [<bibl><ptr target="#oliverioDAI1"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#oliverioDAI2"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The need of a corpusdevoted to the Greek inscriptions of Cyrenaica was already felt. J.J.E. Hondius collected a first group of inscriptions in the <title>Supplementum Epigraphicum Graecum</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#SEG"/></bibl>), volume 9.1 (1939) and a second in volume 9.2 (1944). 
                        Although completed by an index, this comprehensive publication of the inscriptions edited in the years 1912-1935 can of course not be considered as a corpus, and was never intended to be one; it lacks images and, while some new readings were suggested, none were based on access to the original texts [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>: 19-20].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The outbreaks of the Second World War ended archaeological activity in the area and, in due course, the Italian occupation. Gaspare Oliverio, who died in 1956, was unable to publish the inscriptions recovered in the years immediately before the war. His <title>Supplemento Epigrafico Cirenaico</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#SECir"/></bibl>) was not published until 1961-1962 by Giovanni Pugliese Carratelli and Donato Morelli.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The British Military Administration responsible for Cyrenaica until the establishment of the sovereign state of Libya by the United Nations at the end of 1951 preserved the structure of the Italian Antiquities service. The activity of British archaeologists, in particular those working at the British School at Rome, became intense. John Ward-Perkins, the Director, and Joyce M. Reynolds, a student of the school, started to travel in the region and in 1952 they published the <title>Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania</title> [<bibl><ptr target="#jmr-jbwp1952"/></bibl>]. The British Controller of the Antiquities service in the period 1953-1966 was Richard Goodchild who carried out excavations at Taucheira, at Ptolemais, at Cyrene and in some rural sites. 
                        Many Greek and Latin inscriptions were found and published by Goodchild himself alone or with the help of Joyce Reynolds. A corpus of the inscriptions of the Roman period was then first planned, but it never came to light. The achievements of Richard Goodchild include the renewed involvement in excavation of Italian scholars led by Sandro Stucchi as well as the encouragement of other foreign expeditions (the Americans at Ptolemais, the French at Apollonia) and the training of native Libyan archaeologists. 
                        The work of these years and the involvement of the local Department of Antiquities can be appreciated through the Proceedings of the Historical Conference <title>Libya in History</title> held at the University of Libya [Benghazi 1968] and the articles of the new review <title>Libya Antiqua</title> (Tripoli, from 1964). From the epigraphic point of view, mention should be made of the <title>Inscriptions from Cyrene</title> published by Peter Marshall Fraser in 1958 [<bibl><ptr target="#fraser1958"/></bibl>] and the works by Lidio Gasperini [<bibl><ptr target="#gasperini1965"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#gasperini1967a"/></bibl>], the epigraphist of the Italian mission guided by Stucchi.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">After the revolution in 1969 and the rise of Muammar Qadhafi, the Department of Antiquities continued to function side by side with many foreign missions, even though without the opportunity to embark on initiatives of its own as it did in Goodchild's time [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>: 17]. An American mission worked at Cyrene in the sanctuary of Wadi Bil Gadir from 1969 to 1978: the inscriptions found have been published by Joyce Reynolds [<bibl><ptr target="#jmr2012"/></bibl>]. 
                        After Stucchi's death, the Italian mission at Cyrene was directed by Lidiano Bacchielli (1991-1996) and by Mario Luni (1996-2014), the epigraphists being Lidio Gasperini, Gianfranco Paci and Silvia Maria Marengo. In recent years, the epigraphists Emilio Rosamilia and Stefano Struffolino collaborated to the missions of the Universities of Urbino (head Oscar Mei), Chieti (Oliva Menozzi) and Campania (Serena Ensoli). A French mission has been working at Apollonia since 1976, under the direction of François Chamoux (until 1981), André Laronde (1981-2011) and now Vincent Michel. Catherine Dobias-Lalou has been working on inscriptions as a member of the mission since its beginnings. British missions have worked at Benghazi, one in the area of Berenice from 1971 to 1975, another one at Euesperides from 1995 to 2006, while a Polish mission has been working at Ptolemais since 2001.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Some outstanding publications appeared in the seventies and the eighties of the 20th century. Among the most important for the knowledge of new Greek texts and the improvement of old ones, are the two volumes by J. Boardman, J. Hayes, <title>Excavations at Tocra 1963-1965</title> [<bibl><ptr target="#boardman-hayes1966"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#boardman-hayes1973"/></bibl>]; the fundamental monograph <title>Cyrène et la Libye hellénistique. Libykai historiai de l'époque républicaine au principat d'Auguste</title> by the late André Laronde [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>]; and the article <title>Les comptes de démiurges à Cyrène</title> by François Chamoux [<bibl><ptr target="#chamoux1988"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The last 35 years have seen an increase in the epigraphical researches devoted to specific issues concerning the history of the region: political and military events, the composition of the ancient population of Cyrenaica, the contacts with other people from the Mediterranean world, the institutions, the cults, the prosopography and onomastics, the dialect, the original Cyrenean numerals, the archaeology and topography; simultaneously many new inscriptions have been published in authored articles [see the analytical reviews appeared in <title>Quaderni di Archeologia della Libia</title> and in the series <title>L'Africa romana</title>]. The edition of an up to date and authentic corpus of the inscriptions from Greek Cyrenaica couldn't be further postponed.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">The team responsible for the <title>IGCyr</title>-<title>GVCyr</title> corpora and, in particular, the lead epigraphy researcher of the project, Catherine Dobias-Lalou have a long tradition of research devoted to Cyrenaica. As a member of the French archaeological mission in Libya since 1976, Catherine Dobias-Lalou regularly visited the region until the revolution of 2011. Her interest in the inscriptions of Cyrenaica already began in the seventies. 
                        She wrote many articles through the eighties and the nineties concerning the language of the Greek inscriptions, Cyrenean onomastics, the contrast between the Cyrenean dialect and the koine attested in Cyrenaica in the Hellenistic period as well as the specific vocabulary of Cyrenean metrical texts. In 2000 her fundamental monograph <title>Le dialecte des inscriptions grecques de Cyrène</title> appeared. 
                        Other fields of research have in the meanwhile enriched her commitment to Cyrenean inscriptions alongside the continuing linguistic interest, leading to a series of articles on important texts and new inscriptions. Catherine Dobias-Lalou has also been responsible, since 1988, for the section <title>Cyrénaïque et Afrique Mineure</title> of the <title>Bulletin épigraphique</title> in the <title>Revue des études Grecques</title>. Gianfranco Paci and Silvia Maria Marengo have for their part contributed to the development of the epigraphic studies regarding the region, the first thanks to his work on the field and his publications of new texts, the second thanks to her essential <title>Lessico delle iscrizioni greche della Cirenaica</title> [<bibl><ptr target="#marengo1991"/></bibl>] and many articles about old and new inscriptions. Lucia Criscuolo, a historian and papyrologist, has been studying Cyrenaica because of her interests in the reign of the Ptolemies and has contributed to the interpretation of the most important historical inscriptions of Cyrene.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">In the aftermath of the revolution it seemed that Libya was «facing an era of unparelleled change» and it was «greatly to be hoped that this» would have brought «new benefits both to archaeology and to tourism, and that it» would have resulted «in a level of public understanding of history and archaeology amongst the Libyans themselves which they have never previously been invited to participate in.» [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>: 17]. 
                        The <title>IGCyr</title> project was launched in the same period, in the same spirit. In 2017, our conclusion was that «everything is very uncertain since 2013, archaeological expeditions are impossible, most foreign diplomatic missions are closed or displaced to another country; but scholars who are prevented from visiting Libya can take stock of their work at this point and aim to make it more fully available than ever before, in the hope of providing a rich resource for Libyan scholarship in the future».</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Postscript 2023: twelve years after the 2011 revolution, the situation in Libya is still not secured. The members of the Department of Antiquities are highly devoted to their mission of preservation, but the challenge is huge, as they must struggle against both human and natural destruction: new buildings in areas theoretically protected by Unesco and illicit excavations are a constant concern, while members of foreign missions, if allowed, may stay only for a very limited time and cannot help as much as they want. 
                        However, with help of modern technologies of communication, contacts were never cut off and collaboration is still active, leading to publications in the Department’s journal, <title>Libya Antiqua</title>. And collaboration between foreign missions has never proved more effective than in those difficult years, as testified by the present achievement. 
                        The desire to contribute jointly to epigraphic research on Libya has led to the creation of an international network (<title>Libyan Epigraphy Research Network</title>: <ref target="https://libyanepigraphy.org/committees/">LERN</ref>), which goes beyond the former <title>InsLib</title> framework and aims to ensure the continuity of the corpus and its gradual updating on a voluntary basis.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="en">Alice Bencivenni (rev. Charlotte Roueché)</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="it">Viaggiatori e studiosi europei cominciarono a visitare la Cirenaica già nel XVIII secolo, benché la zona, fin dalla sua inclusione nell'impero ottomano nel XVI secolo, fosse di difficile accesso. Come è stato giustamente sottolineato, questi primi viaggiatori erano interessati a copiare iscrizioni come pure - o, a dire il vero, più che - a scoprire antiche rovine [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>: 18].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Il console francese a Tripoli, Claude Le Maire, visitò Cirene nel 1706, fece un breve resoconto del suo viaggio e copiò la prima iscrizione, <ref target="https://ircyr2020.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/en/inscriptions/C.316.html"><title>IRCyr2020</title> C.316</ref> [Le Maire in <bibl><ptr target="#lucas1712"/></bibl>; cf. <bibl><ptr target="#omont1902"/></bibl>]. Granger, pseudonimo di Félix Tourtachot, un chirurgo francese, andò a Cirene negli anni trenta del XVIII secolo e probabilmente copiò tre iscrizioni che furono poi incluse nelle carte di Michel Fourmont, professore al Collège de France [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>: 18-19]. 
                        Nel 1817 il medico italiano Paolo Della Cella fu il primo viaggiatore a visitare in modo approfondito le antichità della Cirenaica, descrivendo in particolare Cirene e Apollonia [<bibl><ptr target="#dellacella1819"/></bibl>]. Grazie alla sua formazione classica, egli fu in grado di copiare iscrizioni greche e latine. 
                        Padre Pacifico da Monte Cassiano visitò la Pentapoli nel 1819 lasciando una breve descrizione del viaggio [pubblicata in <bibl><ptr target="#delaporte1825"/></bibl>] e alcune copie di iscrizioni. In seguito, il pittore francese Jean-Raimond Pacho visitò la Cirenaica nel 1824-1825 e il resoconto dettagliato del suo viaggio, pubblicato dopo la sua morte, cita copie di un gran numero di iscrizioni da Cirene, Taucheira e Barka [<bibl><ptr target="#pacho1827"/></bibl>]. Questi lavori, insieme ad alcune copie del conte danese J.C. Graber de Hemsö, console a Tripoli, e alcune altre, forse quelle di Padre Pacifico, trasmesse a Pietro Negri, console di Sardegna a Tripoli, furono essenziali per l'edizione delle iscrizioni greche della Cirenaica incluse da Johannes Franz e August Boeckh nel terzo volume del <title>Corpus Inscriptionum Graecarum</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#CIG"/></bibl>) [Berlin 1853: pars XXXI nos. 5129-5362b].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">La spedizione sponsorizzata dalla British Admiralty nel 1822 e guidata dai fratelli Frederick e Henry Beechey ebbe, come risultato fondamentale, l'elaborazione di due importanti mappe di Cirene [<bibl><ptr target="#beechey1828"/></bibl>: 404-405; 430-431]. In conseguenza di questo viaggio, il console britannico a Tripoli W. Warrington inviò nel 1826 e nel 1827 due spedizioni guidate dai suoi figli Frederick e H. George Warrington con lo scopo dichiarato di raccogliere antichità: cinque casse, inclusa una iscrizione, arrivarono in Inghilterra [<bibl><ptr target="#luni1998"/></bibl>: 336]. 
                        Al vice-console francese a Tripoli e poi a Benghazi Jean Vattier de Bourville fu assegnata dal suo governo una missione; nel 1847-1848 rilevò alcune iscrizioni nel corso dei suoi scavi a Benghazi, Cirene e Ptolemais (dove rimosse dal muro della fortezza l'iscrizione dell'imperatore bizantino Anastasio ora al Louvre): queste iscrizioni, di cui fu data comunicazione da A.-J. Letronne [<bibl><ptr target="#letronne1828"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#letronne1848"/></bibl>] e che furono ripubblicate da Vattier de Bourville [<bibl><ptr target="#vattier1850"/></bibl>], furono inserite negli <title>Addenda</title> del quarto volume del (<bibl><ptr target="#CIG"/></bibl>) [Berlin 1859].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">La prima spedizione 'scientifica' che scavò in Cirenaica fu quella condotta da R. Murdoch Smith e Edwin A. Porcher nel 1860-1861 [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>]. Essi cominciarono a scavare a Cirene a loro spese, ma in seguito furono sovvenzionati dal governo inglese: circa trenta nuovi testi furono allora scoperti.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Queste nuove iscrizioni greche furono incluse in due importanti collezioni epigrafiche che ne diffusero la conoscenza: nel 1905, <title>Sammlung der griechischen Dialekt-Inschriften</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#SGDI"/></bibl>), di Hermann Collitz e Friedrich Bechtel (III.2, 4833-4870) e, nel 1923, <title>Dialectorum graecarum exempla epigraphica potiora</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#DGE"/></bibl>), di Eduard Schwyzer.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">La successiva spedizione autorizzata a Cirene fu condotta dagli Americani con Richard Norton nel 1910-1911: l'epigrafista del gruppo, Herbert de Cou, fu ucciso per ragioni ignote sullo scavo (11 marzo 1911). Il promettente lavoro della squadra è testimoniato da <title>Inscriptions from the Cyrenaica</title> pubblicato da D.M. Robinson nell'<title>American Journal of Archaeology</title> del 1913 [17, <bibl><ptr target="#robinson1913"/></bibl>: 157-200; alle pagine 193-200 le correzioni del <bibl><ptr target="#CIG"/></bibl> che seguono le note di H. de Cou].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Nello stesso 1910 l'archeologo italiano Federico Halbherr aveva condotto una spedizione in Libia con il supporto del governo italiano e il consenso dei Turchi: Gaetano De Sanctis faceva parte della squadra. Molti apografi di iscrizioni redatti da Halbherr si trovano nel fondo conservato presso l'Accademia Roveretana degli Agiati [<bibl><ptr target="#paci1991"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Dopo l'invasione della Libia nel 1911, gli Italiani cominciarono a scavare regolarmente alla ricerca delle antichità cirenaiche, concentrandosi soprattutto a Cirene, ma anche a Ptolemais e Apollonia, dal 1912 al 1942. Nel 1912 fu creata sul posto la Soprintendenza per le Antichità della Cirenaica e dal 1925 in avanti una Missione Straordinaria fu solita lavorare durante l'estate. Benché collegati con una occupazione militare che produsse inevitabili episodi irrispettosi della conservazione dei resti archeologici, questi scavi regolari portarono un contributo fondamentale alla conoscenza dei siti e della loro epigrafia.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Un gran numero di importanti pubblicazioni apparvero in questo periodo nel <title>Notiziario Archeologico</title> (1915-1927) e nella serie <title>Africa Italiana</title> (1927-1941). Già nel 1925 Silvio Ferri pubblicò alcune grandi iscrizioni come il diagramma di Tolemeo (<ref target=".././igcyr010800">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>010800</ref>) e nel 1928 un numero speciale della <title>Rivista di Filologia e di Istruzione Classica</title> fu interamente dedicato alle iscrizioni di Cirene. Negli anni 1932-1936 furono pubblicati i fondamentali due volumi <title>Documenti antichi dell'Africa italiana</title> di Gaspare Oliverio [<bibl><ptr target="#oliverioDAI1"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#oliverioDAI2"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Già in questa epoca si sentì la necessità di un <foreign>corpus</foreign> dedicato alle iscrizioni greche della Cirenaica. J.J.E. Hondius raccolse un primo gruppo di iscrizioni nel <title>Supplementum Epigraphicum Graecum</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#SEG"/></bibl>), volume 9.1 (1939), e un secondo nel volume 9.2 (1944). Benché corredata da un indice, questa pubblicazione comprensiva di tutti i testi editi negli anni 1912-1935 non può essere considerata un vero <foreign>corpus</foreign> - né fu concepita come tale - a causa della mancanza di immagini e di verifiche di lettura sulle pietre [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>: 19-20].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Gli eventi della Seconda Guerra Mondiale arrestarono l'attività archeologica nella zona e posero fine all'occupazione italiana. Gaspare Oliverio, che morì nel 1956, non riuscì a pubblicare le iscrizioni rinvenute negli anni immediatamente precedenti la guerra. Il suo <title>Supplemento epigrafico cirenaico</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#SECir"/></bibl>) fu edito da Giovanni Pugliese Carratelli e Donato Morelli solo nel 1961-1962.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">L'amministrazione militare britannica, responsabile della Cirenaica fino alla creazione dello stato sovrano di Libia da parte delle Nazioni Unite alla fine del 1951, conservò la struttura della Soprintendenza per le Antichità della Cirenaica. L'attività degli archeologi britannici, in particolare di quelli che lavoravano presso la British School di Roma, divenne intensa. John Ward-Perkins, il Direttore, e Joyce M. Reynolds, una allieva della scuola, cominciarono a viaggiare nella regione e nel 1952 pubblicarono le <title>Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania</title> [<bibl><ptr target="#jmr-jbwp1952"/></bibl>]. 
                        L'ispettore della Soprintendenza nel periodo 1953-1966 era l'inglese Richard Goodchild che condusse scavi a Taucheira, a Ptolemais, a Cirene e in alcuni villaggi rurali. Molte iscrizioni greche e latine furono rinvenute e pubblicate da Goodchild stesso, da solo o in collaborazione con Joyce Reynolds. Un <foreign>corpus</foreign> delle iscrizioni del periodo romano fu allora progettato per la prima volta, ma non ha mai visto la luce. 
                        I meriti di Richard Goodchild comprendono il rinnovato coinvolgimento negli scavi degli Italiani guidati da Sandro Stucchi come pure la sollecitazione di altre spedizioni straniere (gli Americani a Ptolemais, i Francesi ad Apollonia) e l'addestramento di archeologi libici. Il lavoro di questi anni e il coinvolgimento attivo del Dipartimento delle Antichità locale può essere apprezzato negli atti della Historical Conference <title>Libya in History</title> tenuta alla University of Libya [Benghazi 1968] e negli articoli della nuova rivista <title>Libya Antiqua</title> (Tripoli, dal 1964). Dal punto di vista epigrafico, occorre citare <title>Inscriptions from Cyrene</title> pubblicato da Peter Marshall Fraser nel 1958 [<bibl><ptr target="#fraser1958"/></bibl>] e i lavori di Lidio Gasperini [<bibl><ptr target="#gasperini1965"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#gasperini1967a"/></bibl>], l'epigrafista della missione italiana guidata da Stucchi.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Dopo la rivoluzione del 1969 e l'avvento al potere di Muammar Qadhafi, il Dipartimento delle Antichità ha continuato a funzionare accanto a molte missioni straniere, sebbene senza l'opportunità di avviare iniziative autonome come al tempo di Goodchild [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>: 17]. Una missione americana ha lavorato a Cirene nel santuario di Wadi Bil Gadir dal 1969 al 1978: le iscrizioni rinvenute sono state pubblicate da Joyce Reynolds [<bibl><ptr target="#jmr2012"/></bibl>]. 
                        Dopo la morte di Stucchi, la missione italiana a Cirene è stata diretta da Lidiano Bacchielli (1991-1996) e da Mario Luni (1996-2014), con la collaborazione epigrafica di Lidio Gasperini, Gianfranco Paci e Silvia Maria Marengo. Più di recente, gli epigrafisti Emilio Rosamilia e Stefano Struffolino hanno collaborato con le missioni delle Università di Urbino (direzione Oscar Mei), di Chieti (Olivia Menozzi) e della Campania (Serena Ensoli). Dal 1976 una missione francese ha condotto scavi ad Apollonia sotto la direzione di François Chamoux (fino al 1981), André Laronde (1981-2011) e ora Vincent Michel. Catherine Dobias-Lalou ha studiato le iscrizioni come membro della missione fin dai suoi esordi. Missioni inglesi hanno lavorato a Benghazi, una nell'area di Berenice dal 1971 al 1975, un'altra ad Euesperides dal 1995 al 2006, mentre una missione polacca sta lavorando a Ptolemais dal 2001.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Alcune rilevanti pubblicazioni sono apparse negli anni settanta e ottanta del secolo scorso. Per citare solo le più importanti per la conoscenza di nuove iscrizioni greche e il miglioramento di vecchie edizioni, occorre menzionare i due volumi di J. Boardman, J. Hayes, <title>Excavations at Tocra</title> 1963-1965 [<bibl><ptr target="#boardman-hayes1966"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#boardman-hayes1973"/></bibl>]; la fondamentale monografia <title>Cyrène et la Libye hellénistique. Libykai historiai de l'époque républicaine au principat d'Auguste</title> del compianto André Laronde [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>]; l'articolo <title>Les comptes de démiurges à Cyrène</title> di François Chamoux [<bibl><ptr target="#chamoux1988"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Gli ultimi 35 anni hanno visto l'aumento delle ricerche dedicate a specifici temi riguardanti la storia della regione: gli eventi politici e militari, la composizione dell'antica popolazione della Cirenaica, i contatti con altre genti del mondo mediterraneo, le istituzioni, i culti, la prosopografia e l'onomastica, il dialetto, i numerali cirenei, l'archeologia e la topografia; contemporaneamente molte nuove iscrizioni sono state pubblicate in sedi diverse [cf. le rassegne bibliografiche apparse in <title>Quaderni di Archeologia della Libia</title> e nella serie <title>L'Africa romana</title>]. L'edizione di un vero e proprio <foreign>corpus</foreign> aggiornato delle iscrizioni della Cirenaica greca non poteva più essere rinviata.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Il gruppo di ricerca responsabile dei due <foreign>corpora</foreign> <title>IGCyr</title>-<title>GVCyr</title> e, in particolare, l'epigrafista principale del progetto Catherine Dobias-Lalou vantano una lunga tradizione di studi dedicati alla Cirenaica. Membro della missione archeologica francese in Libia dal 1976, Catherine Dobias-Lalou ha regolarmente visitato la regione fino alla rivoluzione del 2011. 
                        Il suo interesse per le iscrizioni della Cirenaica è cominciato già negli anni settanta. Ha scritto molti articoli nel corso degli anni ottanta e novanta riguardanti il linguaggio delle iscrizioni greche, l'onomastica cirenea, il confronto tra il dialetto cireneo e la koiné attestata in Cirenaica in età ellenistica come pure il vocabolario proprio dei testi metrici cirenei. 
                        Nel 2000 è uscita la fondamentale monografia <title>Le dialecte des inscriptions grecques de Cyrène</title>. Altri campi di ricerca hanno nel frattempo arricchito il suo fruttuoso impegno riguardo alle iscrizioni cirenee accanto all'interesse linguistico mai sopito, come provano gli articoli su alcuni testi importanti e le pubblicazioni di inediti. 
                        Catherine Dobias-Lalou è anche responsabile dal 1988 della sezione Cyrénaïque et Afrique Mineure del <title>Bulletin épigraphique</title> nella <title>Revue des études Grecques</title>. Gianfranco Paci e Silvia Maria Marengo hanno entrambi considerevolmente fatto progredire gli studi epigrafici sulla regione, il primo grazie al suo lavoro sul campo e alle sue pubblicazioni di inediti, la seconda grazie al suo imprescindibile <title>Lessico delle iscrizioni greche della Cirenaica</title> [<bibl><ptr target="#marengo1991"/></bibl>] e a diversi articoli su iscrizioni già note o inedite. 
                        Lucia Criscuolo, storica e papirologa, si è occupata della Cirenaica nel corso dei suoi studi sul regno dei Tolemei e ha contribuito alla interpretazione delle più importanti iscrizioni storiche di Cirene.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Subito dopo la rivoluzione sembrava che la Libia stesse «andando incontro ad un'era di cambiamento senza precedenti» e si poteva «sperare davvero che questo» avrebbe portato «nuovi vantaggi sia all'archeologia sia al turismo, e che ciò» avrebbe condotto «i Libici stessi ad un livello di comprensione pubblica delle storia e della archeologia che essi non avevano mai potuto sperimentare in precedenza» [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>: 17; trad. AB]. 
                        Il progetto <title>IGCyr</title> è stato avviato in quello stesso periodo, in quello stesso spirito. Ecco come abbiamo concluso il nostro commento nel 2017: «A partire dal 2013 tutto è molto incerto, le spedizioni archeologiche sono impossibili, la maggior parte delle sedi diplomatiche è chiusa o spostata all'estero. Ora gli studiosi, ai quali si impedisce di andare in Libia, possono comunque fare il punto sul loro lavoro e aspirano a renderlo completamente disponibile ancor più che nel passato, nella speranza di fornire una risorsa utile agli studi futuri sulla Libia».</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it"><foreign>Post scriptum</foreign> 2023: dodici anni dopo la rivoluzione del 2011, la situazione in Libia non è ancora sicura. I membri del Dipartimento delle Antichità sono profondamente impegnati nella loro missione di conservazione, ma devono affrontare un'enorme sfida, dovendo combattere i pericoli che provengono sia dall’uomo sia dalla natura: nuove costruzioni in aree teoricamente protette dall’Unesco e scavi clandestini sono una costante fonte di preoccupazione, mentre i membri delle missioni straniere, se ricevono il permesso, possono rimanere solo per un tempo limitato e non possono fornire tutto l'aiuto che vorrebbero. 
                        Tuttavia, grazie alle nuove tecnologie di comunicazione, i contatti non si sono mai interrotti e la collaborazione rimane attiva, producendo pubblicazioni sulla rivista del Dipartimento, <title>Libya Antiqua</title>. E la collaborazione tra le missioni estere non è mai stata così forte come in questi anni difficili, come dimostra il rinnovato <foreign>corpus</foreign> qui presentato. La volontà di dare un contributo comune alla ricerca epigrafica sulla Libia ha dato vita a una rete internazionale (<title>Libyan Epigraphy Research Network</title>: <ref target="https://libyanepigraphy.org/committees/">LERN</ref>), che va oltre la vecchia struttura <title>InsLib</title> e dovrebbe garantire la continuità dei <foreign>corpora</foreign> e il suo progressivo aggiornamento su base volontaria.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="it">Alice Bencivenni</p>
                    
                    
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Les voyageurs et érudits européens ont commencé à visiter la Cyrénaïque dès le XVIII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle, bien que la région fût d'accès difficile depuis son rattachement à l'Empire ottoman au XVI<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle. Comme on l'a justement souligné, ces premiers voyageurs étaient aussi - et même plus - intéressés par la copie d'inscriptions que par la découverte des ruines antiques [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>: 18].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Le consul français à Tripoli, Claude Le Maire, se rendit à Cyrène en 1706, en tira un bref rapport et copia la première inscription, <ref target="https://ircyr2020.inslib.kcl.ac.uk/en/inscriptions/C.316.html"><title>IRCyr2020</title> C.316</ref> [Le Maire in <bibl><ptr target="#lucas1712"/></bibl>; cf. <bibl><ptr target="#omont1902"/></bibl>]. Granger, pseudonyme de Félix Tourtachot, un chirurgien français, se rendit à Cyrène dans les années trente du XVIII<hi rend="superscript">e</hi> siècle et copia probablement les trois inscriptions qui se retrouvèrent par la suite dans les papiers de Michel Fourmont, professeur au Collège de France [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>: 18-19]. En 1817, le médecin italien Paolo Della Cella fut le premier voyageur à faire une visite détaillée des antiquités de Cyrénaïque, décrivant en particulier Cyrène et Apollonia [<bibl><ptr target="#dellacella1819"/></bibl>]. Grâce à sa formation classique, il fut en mesure de copier des inscriptions grecques et latines. Le Père Pacifique du Mont-Cassin visita la Pentapole en 1819 et laissa une brève description de son voyage [publiée par <bibl><ptr target="#delaporte1825"/></bibl>] et quelques copies d'inscriptions. Par la suite, le peintre français Jean-Raimond Pacho visita la Cyrénaïque en 1824-1825 et le compte rendu détaillé de son voyage, publié après sa mort, contient des copies de nombreuses inscriptions de Cyrène, Taucheira et Barka [<bibl><ptr target="#pacho1827"/></bibl>]. Ces travaux, joints à quelques copies du comte danois J.C. Graber de Hemsö, consul à Tripoli, et à quelques autres, probablement celles du Père Pacifique, transmises à Pietro Negri, consul de Sardaigne à Tripoli, constituèrent le matériel essentiel pour l'édition des inscriptions grecques de Cyrénaïque recueillies par Johannes Franz et August Boeckh dans le troisième tome du <title>Corpus Inscriptionum Graecarum</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#CIG"/></bibl>) [Berlin 1853: pars XXXI, n° 5129-5362b].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">L'expédition financée par la British Admiralty en 1822 et conduite par les frères Frederick et Henry Beechey eut pour résultat fondamental l'élaboration de deux importants plans de Cyrène [<bibl><ptr target="#beechey1828"/></bibl>: 404-405; 430-431]. A la suite de ce voyage, le consul britannique à Tripoli W. Warrington monta en 1826 et 1827 deux expéditions, conduites par ses fils Frederick et H. George Warrington, avec l'objectif affiché de recueillir des antiquités: cinq caisses, y compris une inscription, arrivèrent en Angleterre [<bibl><ptr target="#luni1998"/></bibl>: 336]. Le vice-consul français à Tripoli, puis à Benghasi, Jean Vattier de Bourville, obtint de son gouvernement un ordre de mission et en 1847-1848 releva quelques inscriptions au cours de ses fouilles à Benghasi, Cyrène et Ptolémaïs (où il arracha du mur de la forteresse l'inscription de l'empereur byzantin Anastase aujourd'hui conservée au Louvre): ces inscriptions, communiquées par A.-J. Letronne [<bibl><ptr target="#letronne1828"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#letronne1848"/></bibl>], republiées par Vattier de Bourville [<bibl><ptr target="#vattier1850"/></bibl>], furent insérées dans des Addenda au tome IV du <bibl><ptr target="#CIG"/></bibl> [Berlin 1859].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">La première expédition "scientifique" de fouilles à Cyrène est celle que dirigèrent R. Murdoch Smith et Edwin A. Porcher en 1860-1861 [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>]. Ils commencèrent à fouiller à Cyrène à leurs propres frais, mais furent par la suite subventionnés par le gouvernement anglais: une trentaine de nouveaux textes furent alors découverts.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Ces nouvelles inscriptions grecques prirent place dans deux importants recueils épigraphiques qui en répandirent la connaissance: en 1905, la <title>Sammlung der griechischen Dialekt-Inschriften</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#SGDI"/></bibl>) d'Hermann Collitz et Friedrich Bechtel (III.2, 4833-4870) et en 1923 les <title>Dialectorum graecarum exempla potiora</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#DGE"/></bibl>) d'Eduard Schwyzer.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">L'expédition officielle suivante fut menée à Cyrène par des Américains, sous la direction de Richard Norton en 1910-1911: l'épigraphiste du groupe, Herbert de Cou, fut tué sur place dans des circonstances obscures (11 mars 1911). Le travail prometteur de cette équipe est illustré par les Inscriptions from the Cyrenaica publiées par D.M. Robinson dans l'American Journal of Archaeology de 1913 [17, <bibl><ptr target="#robinson1913"/>: 157-200</bibl>; cf. en outre pp. 193-200, les corrections apportées au <bibl><ptr target="#CIG"/></bibl> d'après les notes de H. de Cou].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">La même année 1910 l'archéologue italien Federico Halbherr avait dirigé une mission en Libye avec l'appui du gouvernement italien et l'accord des Turcs: Gaetano De Sanctis faisait partie du groupe. De nombreuses copies d'inscriptions exécutées par Halbherr se trouvent dans le fond conservé à l'Accademia Roveretana degli Agiati [<bibl><ptr target="#paci1991"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Après l'invasion de la Libye en 1911, les Italiens se mirent à travailler régulièrement à la recherche des antiquités cyrénéennes, principalement à Cyrène, mais aussi à Ptolémaïs et Apollonia, de 1912 à 1942. En 1912 fut créée sur place la Soprintendenza per le Antichità della Cirenaica et à partir de 1925 une Mission Extraordinaire prit l'habitude de travailler durant l'été. Bien que cohabitant avec une force d'occupation militaire, ce qui entraîna inévitablement des incidents mettant en danger la préservation des vestiges archéologiques, ces fouilles régulières fournirent une contribution fondamentale à la connaissance des sites et de leur épigraphie.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Un grand nombre de publications importantes parurent durant cette période dans le <title>Notiziario Archeologico</title> (1915-1927) et dans la série <title>Africa Italiana</title> (1927-1941). Dès 1925, Silvio Ferri publia quelques grandes inscriptions comme le diagramma de Ptolémée (<ref target=".././igcyr010800">IGCyr<hi rend="superscript">2</hi>010800</ref>) et en 1928 un numéro spécial de la <title>Rivista di Filologia e di Istruzione Classica</title> fut entièrement consacré aux inscriptions de Cyrène. Dans les années 1932 à 1936 Gaspare Oliverio publia les deux volumes fondamentaux de <title>Documenti antichi dell'Africa Italiana</title> [<bibl><ptr target="#oliverioDAI1"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#oliverioDAI2"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Dès cette époque la nécessité d'un corpus consacré aux inscriptions grecques de la Cyrénaïque se fit sentir. J.J.E. Hondius rassembla un premier groupe d'inscriptions dans le <title>Supplementum Epigraphicum Graecum</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#SEG"/></bibl>), 9, fascicule 1 (1939) et un second dans le fascicule 2 (1944). Bien que munie d'index, cette publication globale de tous les textes publiés entre 1912 et 1935 ne peut être considérée comme un véritable corpus - il ne fut pas conçu ainsi - puisqu'elle ne repose pas sur une vérification des lectures sur les pierres et ne comporte aucune image [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>: 19-20].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Les évènements de la seconde guerre mondiale interrompirent l'activité archéologique dans la région et mirent fin à l'occupation italienne. Gaspare Oliverio, qui mourut en 1956, ne réussit pas à publier les inscriptions découvertes dans les années précédant immédiatement la guerre. Son <title>Supplemento epigrafico cirenaico</title> (<bibl><ptr target="#SECir"/></bibl>) fut édité par Giovanni Pugliese Carratelli et Donato Morelli seulement en 1961-1962.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">L'administration militaire britannique, responsable de la Cyrénaïque jusqu'à la création par les Nations Unies à la fin de 1951 de l'État souverain de Libye, conserva la structure de la Surintendance des Antiquités de Cyrénaïque. L'activité des archéologues britanniques, en particulier ceux qui appartenaient à l'Ecole Britannique de Rome, fut intense. 
                        Son directeur, John Ward-Perkins, et Joyce M. Reynolds, une élève de l'Ecole, commencèrent à voyager dans la région et en 1952 publièrent les <title>Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania</title> [<bibl><ptr target="#jmr-jbwp1952"/></bibl>]. L'inspecteur de la Surintendance pour la période 1953-1966 fut Richard Goodchild, qui exécuta des fouilles à Taucheira, à Ptolémaïs, à Cyrène et sur quelques sites ruraux. 
                        De nombreuses inscriptions grecques et latines furent découvertes et publiées par Goodchild lui-même, seul ou en collaboration avec Joyce Reynolds. Un corpus des inscriptions de la période romaine fut alors projeté pour la première fois, mais n'a pas été mené à bien. Il faut porter au crédit de Richard Goodchild d'avoir incité les archéologues italiens à revenir fouiller sous la direction de Sandro Stucchi, d'avoir invité d'autres missions étrangères (des Américains à Ptolémaïs, des Français à Apollonia) et aussi d'avoir formé des archéologues libyens. 
                        Le travail de ces années-là et l'engagement actif du Département libyen des Antiquités peut être apprécié à travers les actes du congrès international Libya in History tenu à l'Université de Libye [Benghasi 1968] et dans les articles de la nouvelle revue <title>Libya Antiqua</title> (Tripoli, depuis 1964). Du point de vue de l'épigraphie, il faut citer les <title>Inscriptions from Cyrene</title> publiées par P.M. Fraser en 1958 [<bibl><ptr target="#fraser1958"/></bibl>] et le travail épigraphique de Lidio Gasperini [<bibl><ptr target="#gasperini1965"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#gasperini1967a"/></bibl>] au sein de la mission Stucchi.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Après la révolution de 1969 et l'arrivée au pouvoir de Muammar Qadhafi, le Département des Antiquités a continué à fonctionner en collaboration avec des missions étrangères, même si celles-ci ne disposaient pas dans leur travail de la même autonomie que du temps de Goodchild [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>: 17]. 
                        Une mission américaine a travaillé à Cyrène dans le sanctuaire de l'ouadi Bil Gadir de 1969 à 1978: les inscriptions découvertes ont été publiées par Joyce Reynolds [<bibl><ptr target="#jmr2012"/></bibl>]. Après la mort de Stucchi, la mission italienne à Cyrène a été dirigée par Lidiano Bacchielli (1991-1996), puis par Mario Luni (1996-2014), les épigraphistes étant Lidio Gasperini, Gianfranco Paci et Silvia Maria Marengo. Plus récemment, les épigraphistes Emilio Rosamilia et Stefano Struffolino ont collaboré aux missions des Universités d'Urbino (direction Oscar Mei), de Chieti (Oliva Menozzi) et de Campanie (Serena Ensoli). Une mission française travaille à Apollonia depuis 1976 sous la direction de François Chamoux (jusqu'en 1981), d'André Laronde (1981-2011) et maintenant de Vincent Michel. 
                        Catherine Dobias-Lalou a travaillé sur les inscriptions en tant que membre de cette mission depuis ses débuts. Des missions britanniques ont travaillé à Benghasi, l'une sur le site de Bérénikè de 1971 à 1975, l'autre sur le site d'Euhespérides de 1995 à 2006, tandis qu'une mission polonaise travaille à Ptolémaïs depuis 2001.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Quelques publications remarquables ont paru dans les années soixante-dix et quatre-vingt du siècle dernier. Pour ne citer que les plus importantes pour la connaissance de nouvelles inscriptions grecques et l'amélioration d'anciennes éditions, il convient de citer les deux volumes de J. Boardman et J. Hayes, <title>Excavations at Tocra</title> 1963-1965 [<bibl><ptr target="#boardman-hayes1966"/></bibl>; <bibl><ptr target="#boardman-hayes1973"/></bibl>]; la monographie fondamentale <title>Cyrène et la Libye hellénistique. Libykai historiai, de l'époque républicaine au principat d'Auguste</title>, par le regretté André Laronde [<bibl><ptr target="#laronde1987"/></bibl>]; l'article <title>Les comptes des démiurges à Cyrène</title> par François Chamoux [<bibl><ptr target="#chamoux1988"/></bibl>].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Les trente-cinq dernières années ont vu le développement des recherches consacrées à des thèmes spécifiques concernant l'histoire de la région: évènements politiques et militaires, composition de la population de la Cyrénaïque, contacts avec les autres peuples du monde méditerranéen, institutions, cultes, prosopographie et onomastique, dialecte, numérologie cyrénéenne, archéologie et topographie; en même temps, de nombreuses inscriptions nouvelles ont été publiées en des lieux divers [cf. les récapitulations bibliographiques parues dans les <title>Quaderni di Archeologia della Libia</title> et dans la série <title>L'Africa romana</title>]. L'édition d'un véritable corpus des inscriptions de la Cyrénaïque grecque ne pouvait plus attendre.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Le groupe de recherche responsable des deux corpus IGCyr et GVCyr, et en particulier l'épigraphiste principale, Catherine Dobias-Lalou, ont une longue expérience en épigraphie cyrénéenne. Membre de la mission archéologique française en Libye depuis 1976, Catherine Dobias-Lalou a effectué des séjours réguliers dans la région jusqu'à la révolution de 2011. Son intérêt pour les inscriptions cyrénéennes remonte aux années 1970. 
                        Elle a écrit de nombreux articles au cours des années quatre-vingt et quatre-vingt-dix sur la langue des inscriptions grecques, l'onomastique cyrénéenne, la concurrence entre le dialecte cyrénéen et la koiné dans les inscriptions cyrénéennes de la période hellénistique, aussi bien que sur le vocabulaire spécifique des textes métriques. En 2000 a paru la monographie fondamentale Le dialecte des inscriptions grecques de Cyrène. 
                        Entre temps, sans pour autant abandonner le domaine linguistique, elle a diversifié ses recherches sur l'épigraphie cyrénéenne, comme le prouve une série d'articles sur des textes importants et quelques publications d'inédits. Catherine Dobias-Lalou est aussi responsable de la section Cyrénaïque et Afrique mineure du B<title>ulletin épigraphique</title> dans la <title>Revue des Études Grecques</title> depuis 1988. 
                        De leur côté, Gianfranco Paci et Silvia Maria Marengo ont l'un et l'autre fait considérablement avancer les études épigraphiques sur la région, le premier par son travail sur le terrain et ses publications d'inédits, la seconde par son irremplaçable <title>Lessico delle iscrizioni greche della Cirenaica</title> [<bibl><ptr target="#marengo1991"/></bibl>] et par divers articles sur des inscriptions déjà connues ou sur des inédits. Lucia Criscuolo, historienne et papyrologue, s'est occupée de la Cyrénaïque aussi dans ses études sur le règne des Ptolemées et a contribué à l'interprétation des plus importantes inscriptions historiques de Cyrène.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Juste après la révolution, il semblait que la Libye "allait vers une période de changement sans précédent" et que "l'on pouvait nourrir un grand espoir que cela" apporterait "de nouveaux avantages à l'archéologie et au tourisme" et aboutirait "chez les Libyens eux-mêmes à une prise de conscience de leur histoire et de leur patrimoine archéologique à un degré auquel on ne les avait jamais conviés" [<bibl><ptr target="#kenrick2013"/></bibl>: 17; trad. CDL]. 
                        Le projet IGCyr a débuté au même moment, dans le même esprit. Nous clôturions ainsi notre propos en 2017 : «Tout est incertain depuis 2013, les missions archéologiques ne sont plus possibles, la plupart des missions diplomatiques sont fermées ou déplacées dans un autre pays. Maintenant les savants, qui sont empêchés de visiter la Libye, peuvent faire le point sur leur travail et aspirent donc à le rendre complètement disponible encore plus que dans le passé, dans l'espoir de produire une ressource utile aux études futures sur la Libye».</p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Postcriptum 2023 : douze ans après la révolution de 2011, la situation en Libye n’est pas encore sécurisée. Les membres du Département des Antiquités se consacrent pleinement à leur mission de préservation, mais font face à un énorme défi, car ils doivent combattre des risques à la fois humains et naturels : nouvelles constructions dans des zones théoriquement protégées par l’Unesco et fouilles clandestines sont un sujet constant de préoccupation, tandis que les membres des missions étrangères, s’ils en reçoivent l’autorisation, ne peuvent séjourner que pour un temps limité et ne peuvent pas apporter toute l’aide qu’ils souhaiteraient. 
                        Cependant, grâce aux nouvelles technologies de la communication, les contacts n’ont jamais été rompus et la collaboration reste active, conduisant à des publications dans la revue du Département, <title>Libya Antiqua</title>. Et la collaboration entre les missions étrangères n’a jamais été aussi poussée que pendant ces années difficiles, comme en témoigne le corpus renouvelé que nous présentons ici. La volonté de contribuer en commun aux travaux d’épigraphie sur la Libye a donné naissance à un réseau international (<title>Libyan Epigraphy Research Network</title> : <ref target="https://libyanepigraphy.org/committees/">LERN</ref>), qui dépasse l’ancien cadre <title>InsLib</title> et devrait assurer la pérennité des corpus et leur mise à jour progressive sur la base du volontariat. </p>
                    <p xml:lang="fr">Alice Bencivenni (trad. Catherine Dobias-Lalou)</p>
                    
                    <p xml:lang="ar">بدأ الرحالة والبُحاث الأوروبيون زيارة كيرينايكي بالفعل في القرن الثامن عشرالميلادي، على الرغم من صعوبة الوصول إلى المنطقة منذ أن ضُمت للإمبراطورية العثمانيون في القرن السادس عشر، وكان هؤلاء الرحالة الأوائل يرغبون في نسخ النقوش، وفي كثير من الأحيان كان طموحهم أكبر، فكانوا يتطلعون  إلى التعرف على الآثار القديمة [Laronde 1987: 18]، فقد زار القنصل الفرنسي في طرابلس، كلود لومير(Claude Le Maire) كيريني سنة 1706، وكتب عنها باختصار وقام بنسخ أول نقش هو (رابط إلى IRCyr2020 C.316) [Le Maire in Lucas 1712; cf. Omont 1902] ، كما ذهب الطبيب الفرنسي جرانيي (Granger)، تحت الاسم المستعار فيليكس توركوت (Félix Tourtachot) الى مدينة كيريني في الثلاثينيات من القرن الثامن عشر، ونسخ تقريباً ثلاثة نقوش أضيفت في وقت لاحق إلى أوراق ميشيل فورمو(Michel Fourmont) أستاذ الكلية الفرنسية (Collège de France) [Laronde 1987: 18-19]. ويُعد الطبيب الإيطالي باولو ديلا شيلا (Paolo Della Cella) أول رحالة يقوم بزيارة واسعة لأثار كيرينايكي وذلك خلال عام 1817م، حيث قدم على وجه الخصوص وصفًا كيريني وأبولونيا [Della Cella 1819]، وحيث أنه متحصل على قسط جيد من التعليم الكلاسيكي تمكن من نسخ نقوش مكتوبة باللغتين الإغريقية واللاتينية. وفي عام 1819 زار الأب باسيفيكو (Pacifico) من مونتي كاسيانو (Monte Cassiano) المدن الخمس (Pentapolis) وترك وصفاً موجزاً لذلك مصحوباً ببعض النقوش المنسوخة [نُشر في Delaporte 1825]. وفي وقت لاحق زار الرسام الفرنسي جـان-ريـمون باشو (Jean-Raimond Pacho) كيرينايكي في الفترة ما بين عامي 1824-1825 حيث قدم تقريراً مفصلاً لرحلته التي نشرت بعد وفاته، مشيراً إلى قيامه بنسخ عدد كبير من النقوش من كيريني وتاوخيرا وباركي [Pacho 1827]. كل هذه الأعمال، بالإضافة إلى بعض النسخ الأخرى للدنماركي جرابر ديهيمسو (J.C. Graber de Hemsö)، الذي كان قنصلاً في طرابلس، والبعض الآخر الذي ربما منها تلك التي أعدها الأب باسيفيكو(Father Pacifico) سلمت إلى قنصل سردينيا في طرابلس بيترو نيجري (Pietro Negri). وكانت هذه جميعاً المصادر الرئيسية التي تضمنتها الطبعة الخاصة بنقوش كيرينـايكي الإغـريقـية  الـمـعـدة التي ضمنهـا كـل مـن يوهـانس فرانز(Johannes Franz) وأغسـطس بـويكـه (August Boeckh) في المجلد الثالث من مجموعة النقوش الإغريقية ("CIG"Corpus Inscriptionum Graecarum:) [Berlin 1853: pars XXXI nos.5129-5362b].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وفي عـام 1822 دعـمت الـبحرية الـبريطانية رحـلة استـكشافية بقيادة الأخوين فريدريك وهنري بيتشي (Frederick and H. George Beechey) كانت حصيلتها الأولية رسم خريطتين مهمتين لكيريني [Beechey 1828: 404-405; 430-431]. ، وقد دفعت هذه الرحلة، وليام وارينقتون (W. Warrington) نائب القنصل البريطاني في طرابلس إلى إرسال بعثتين في عامي 1826 و1827 مع الإعلان بأن الغرض منهما هوتجميع الآثار، وقد كانتا تحت إشراف ابنيه فريدريك وهانمير جورج وارينقتون (Frederick and H. George Warrington). ومن نتائج هذا العمل نقل نقشاً واحداً إلى انجلترا حيث وُزع بين خمسة صناديق [Luni 1998: 336]. كُلف أيضاً نائب القنصل الفرنسي في طرابلس ثم في بنغازي جان فاتيه ديبورفيل (Jean Vattier de Bourville) من قبل حكومته بمهمة في السنوات 1847-1848، تضمنت ضرورة الاهتمام ببعض النقوش خلال الحفريات التي كان يجريها في بنغازي وكيريني وطلميثة، حيث أزال نقش الإمبراطور البيزنطي أنستاسيوس من جدار الحصن في طلميثة ونقله الى فرنسا ومعروض الآن في متحف اللوفر. هذه النقـوش، أشـار إليها لاتـروني (A.-J. Letronne) [1848; 1848-1849] وأعـاد نشـرها فاتيه ديـبورفيل (Vattier de Bourville)، وأدرجت في ملاحق (Addenda) المجلد الرابع من CIG [Berlin 1859].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وتُعد بعثتة التنقيب التي قادها روبيرت مردوك سميث (R. Murdoch Smith) وإدوين أ. بورشر (Edwin A. Porcher) في عامي 1860 و1861 أول حفريات أثرية "علمية" في كيرينايكي [Kenrick 2013] حيث استهلا التنقيب في مدينة كيريني على نفقتهم الخاصة، ثم في وقت لاحق قامت الحكومة البريطانية بتمويلهم، وقد اكُتشفا في هذه الحفريات حوالي ثلاثين نصاً جديداً.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وقد أدرجت هذه النقوش الإغريقية الجديدة في مجموعتين مهمتين خاصة بالنقوش الأمر الذي جعلها معروفة لجمهور أوسع وهما كما يلي:
1905, the Sammlung der griechischen Dialekt-Inschriften (SGDI), by Hermann Collitz and Friedrich Bechtel (III.2, 4833-4870); 1923, the Dialectorum graecarum exempla epigraphica potiora (DGE), by Eduard Schwyzer.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">شكل الأميركيون بقيادة ريتشارد نورتون (Richard Norton) في سنتي 1910 -1911 البعثة التالية المخولة للعمل بمدينة كيريني، وأثناء الحفريات في 11 مارس 1911 ولأسباب غير معروفة اغتيل هيربرت ديكو (Herbert de Cou) دراس النقوش في البعثة بطلق ناري، وقد اتضحت نتائج العمل الواعد للبعثة من خلال المقال الذي قدمه د. م. روبنسون (D.M. Robinson) بعنوان (نقوش من كيرينايكي) في عام 1913 المنشور في المجلة الأمريكية لعلم الآثار
The American Journal of Archaeology [17, 1913: 157-200; أنظر. 193-200 لتصحيحات CIG التي تلت ملاحظات H. de Cou].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">في العام نفسه 1910، قاد عالم الآثار الإيطالي فيديريكو هالبير (Federico Halbherr) بعثة إلى ليبيا بدعم من الحكومة الإيطالية وبمُباركة الأتراك، وقد كان جايتانو ديسانكتيس (Gaetano De Sanctis) ضمن الفريق، ويمكن إيجاد العديد من رسومات النقوش التي أعدها هالبير (Halbherr) ضمن محفوظاته المودعة في Accademia Roveretana degli Agiati [Paci 1991].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">بدأ الإيطاليون بعد غزوهم ليبيا في عام 1911، بالتقصي حول آثار كيرينايكي بشكل ممنهج، خاصة في كيريني (شحات) بالإضافة إلى طلميثة وأبولونيا (سوسة) في الفترة ما بين من 1912 حتى 1942. ففي عام 1912 أُنشىء مكتب لإدارة الآثار في كيرينايكي، ومنذ عام 1925 فصاعدا شكلت بعثة اثرية استثنائية (Extraordinary Mission) تعمل بالإقليم في كل صيف. رغم ارتباط هذه الحفريات المنتظمة بالاحتلال العسكري الذي أدى إلى حدوث مشاكل لم يكن بالامكان تجنبها، منها عدم الاهتمام أو اظهارعدم الاكتراث بوجوب الحفاظ على البقايا الأثرية، فقد كان لهذه الحفريات اسهاماً فعلياً في معرفة المواقع والنقوش الموجودة بها.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">ظهرت الكثير من المنشورات المهمة خلال هذه الفترة في المجلة الإيطالية المُسماه أخبار أثرية (1915-1927 Notiziario Archeologico)، وفي سلسلة أفريقيا الإيطالية (1927-1941 Africa Italiana)، وبالفعل نشر سيلفيو فيري (Silvio Ferri) في عام 1925 بعض النصوص الأساسية مثل دياجراما بطليموس (رابط إلى IGCyr²  010800)، وصدر في عام  1928 عدد خاص من (Rivista di Filologia e di Istruzione Classica) كُرس  بالكامل لنقوش من كيرينايكي، بالإضافة إلى ذلك نشر اوليفيريو (Gaspare Oliverio) في الفترة 1930-1936 مجلدين أساسيين عُرفا باسم Documenti antichi dell'Africa.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">إن الشعور بضرورة تخصيص جسم يجمع النقوش الإغريقية الكيرينايكية صار أمرأ ملحاٌ. حيث جمع ج. ج. إ. هنديوس (J.J.E. Hondius) المجموعة الأولى من النقوش في المجلد (19. (SEG, Supplementum Epigraphicum Graecum عام 1939، والثانية في المجلد (9.2 (SEG في عام 1944، وعلى الرغم من أن هذا النشرالشامل للنقوش المُعد في السنوات ما بين 1912-1935 قد استكمل بفهرس، إلا أنه لا يمكن اعتباره مجموعة واحدة ولم يُعد ليكون كذلك، حيث يفتقد إلى الصور، وعلى الرغم من اقتراح بعض القراءات الجديدة فإن أياً منها لم يكن مبنياً على معاينة مباشرة بالنصوص الأصلية [Laronde 1987: 19-20].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">باندلاع الحرب العالمية الثانية انتهى الاحتلال الإيطالي لليبيا وتوقف النشاط الأثري لفترة زمنية، فلم يتمكن  غاسباري أوليفيريو(Gaspare Oliverio) الذي توفي في عام 1956 من نشر النقوش المكتشفة في السنوات التي سبقت الحرب مباشرة، حيث لم يُنشر عمله المسمى (SECir) "Supplemento Epigrafico Cirenaico " إلا في عامي 1961-1962 بواسطة جيوفاني بوغليسي كارتيلي (Giovanni Pugliese Carratelli) ودوناتو موريلي (Donato Morelli).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">أبقت الإدارة العسكرية البريطانية المسؤولة عن كيرينايكي على التركيبة الإيطالية لمصلحة الآثار حتى إقامة دولة مستقلة في ليبيا من قبل الأمم المتحدة في نهاية عام 1951، وقد كثف العلماء الإنجليز نشاطهم الآثاري خاصة أولئك العاملين في المدرسة البريطانية في روما. بدأ كل من مدير المدرسة جون وارد بيركنز(John Ward Perkins) والطالبة جويس م. رينولدز (Joyce M. Reynolds) بالسفر إلي ليبيا، وفي عام 1952 قاما بنشر نقوش إقليم المدن الثلاث الرومانية (Inscriptions of Roman Tripolitania). وكان ريتشارد غودتشايلد (Richard Goodchild) المراقب الإنجليزي لمصلحة الآثار في الفترة 1953-1966، قد نفذ أعمال تنقيب في توكرة وطلميثة وكيريني وفي بعض المواقع الريفية، حيث عثر على العديد من النقوش الإغريقية واللاتينية وقام بنشرها إما بمفرده أو بمساعدة من جويس رينولدز(Joyce Reynolds)، ولذا خُطط  في البداية لإعداد مجموعة لنقوش الفترة الرومانية لكنها لم تبصر النور. وتتضمن إنجازات غودتشايلد تجديد انخراط العلماء الإيطاليين في الحفريات تحت إشراف ساندرو ستوكي (Sandro Stucchi)، فضلاً عن تشجيع البعثات الأجنبية الأخرى كالأميركية في طلميثة والفرنسية في أبولونيا، بالإضافة إلى تدريب آثريين ليبيين. إن عمل هـذه السنوات ومشـاركة مصلحـة الآثار المحلية يمكن تقديره مـن خلال وقــائع المؤتمر التاريخي (ليبيا في التاريخ Libya in History ) الذي عُقد عام 1968 في الجامعة الليبية  ببنغازي والمقالات المنشورة في مجلة ليبيا القديمة Libya Antiqua  – طرابلس، التي بدأت بالصدور عام 1964. وفيما يتعلق بالنقوش، ينبغي الإشارة  هنا إلى نقوش كيريني التي نشرها بيتر مارشال فريزر(Peter Marshall Fraser) عام 1958 وكذلك أعمال ليديو جاسبيريني باحث النقوش بالبعثة الايطالية وأشرف عليها ستوكي (1965؛ 1967:Lidio Gasperini).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">
بعد الثورة في عام 1969 وبروز معمر القذافي، واصلت مصلحة الآثار العمل جنبا إلى جنب مع العديد من البعثات الأجنبية، على الرغم من عدم حصولها على فرصة اتخاذ مبادرات من تلقاء نفسها كما كانت في وقت غودتشايلد (Goodchild) [Kenrick 2013: 17]، حيث عملت بعثة أمريكية في مدينة كيريني في الحرم الموجود بوادي بالغدير في السنوات 1969-1978 وقامت جويس رينولدز(Joyce Reynolds) في عام 2012 بنشر النقوش التي عُثر عليها هناك، أما البعثة الإيطالية في كيريني فقد ترأسها بعد وفاة Stucchi ستوكي، ليديانو باكيلي (Lidiano Bacchielli) في الفترة من 1991حتى 1996، ثم ماريو لوني خلال الأعوام من 1996 إلى 2012، وكان ليديو جاسبيريني (Lidio Gasperini) وجيانفرانكو باتشي (Gianfranco Paci) وسيلفيا ماريا مارينقو(Silvia Maria Marengo). في السنوات الأخيرة ، تعاون دارسو النقوش إميليو روزاميليا (Emilio Rosamilia) وستيفانو ستروفولينو (Stefano Struffolino) مع بعثات من جامعة أوربينو (برئاسة أوسكار مي Oscar Mei) وكييتي (برئاسة أوليفا مينوزي Oliva Menozzi) وكامبانيا (برأسة سيرينا إنسولي Serena Ensoli). كما عملت بعثة فرنسية في أبولونيا بإشراف فرانسوا شامو (François Chamoux) منذ عام 1976 واستمرت حتى عام 1981 ثم أشرف عليها أندريه لاروند (André Laronde) في الفترة مابين  1981 و2011  أما الآن فيشرف عليها فنسن ميشيل (Vincent Michel)ن وقد اختصت كاثرين دوبياس- لالو (Catherine Dobias-Lalou) بدراسة النقوش بصفتها عضواً في البعثة منذ بداياتها،  وفيما يتعلق بالبعثات البريطانية فقد عملت في مدينة بنغازي، واحدة كانت في موقع برنيكي في السنوات من 1971 إلى 1975، وأخرى في يوسبيريديس خلال المدة بين 1995 و2006، في حين شرعت البعثة البولندية العمل في طلميثة منذ عام 2001.
</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">ظهرت بعض المنشورات المميزة  في سبعينيات وثمانينيات القرن العشرين، ومن أهمها في مجال النقوش دراسة النصوص الإغريقية الجديدة وكذلك تطوير القديمة منها، مجلدين أعدا من قبل جون بوردمان (J. Boardman) وهايز (J. Hayes) تحت عنوان (Excavations at Tocra 1963-1965) [London 1966, 1973]، وعمل أندريه لاروند (André Laronde) الهام بعنوان:
Cyrène et la Libye hellénistique. Libykai historiai de l'époque républicaine au principat d'Auguste [Paris 1987].
بالإضافة إلى مقال فرانسوا شامو(François Chamoux) تحت عنوان (Les comptes de démiurges à Cyrène) [Neuchâtel 1988].</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وقد شهدت السنوات الخمس وثلاثين الأخيرة زيادة في الأبحاث الخاصة بالنقوش لاسيما تلك المتعلقة بقضايا معينة مرتبطة بتاريخ الإقليم، مثل الأحداث السياسية والعسكرية والتركيبة السكانية القديمة في كيرينايكي  والاتصالات مع شعوب أخرى من عالم البحر المتوسط والمؤسسات والعبادات و البروسوبوقرافيا (prosopography) والتسميات onomastics واللهجة والأرقام الكيرينية الأصلية والآثار والطبوغرافيا، ونُشرت في الوقت نفسه العديد من النقوش الجديدة في مقالات [انظر المـراجـعـات التحليلية التي ظـهـرت في Quaderni di Archeologia della Libia romana وفي سلسلة L'Africa romana . إن الطبعة الحديثة التي توثق مجموعة نقوش كيرينايكي الإغريقية لا يمكن تأجيلها أكثرمن ذلك.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">يتمتع الفريق الذي يقوم بإعداد مجموعتي  IGCyr وGVCyr  بباع طويل في الأبحاث المكرسة لكيرينايكي وعلى وجه الخصوص، وقد قامت كاثرين دوبياس- لالو (Catherine Dobias-Lalou) الباحثة التي تقود مشروع النقوش بصفتها عضواً في البعثة الأثرية الفرنسية في ليبيا منذ عام 1976، بزيارت منتظمة للإقليم حتى قيام الثورة عام 2011. وقد بدأ اهتمامها الفعلي بنقوش كيرينايكي في سبعينيات القرن الماضي حيث كتبت العديد من المقالات خلال الثمانينيات والتسعينيات المتتعلقة بلغة النقوش الإغريقية والتسميات  الكيرينية والاختلاف بين اللهجة الكيرينية  والكويني (koiné)- التي ظهرت بكيرينايكي خلال العصر الهللنستي، فضلا عن دراسة المفردات الخاصة بنصوص الشعر الكيريني، وفي عام 2000 صدرعملها الشامل المتخصص حول اللهجة التي كتبت بها نقوش كيريني بعنوان (Le dialecte des inscriptions grecques de Cyrène)، ولها في ذات الوقت أبحاث في مجالات أخرى أثرت التزامها نحو نقوش كيريني إلى جانب استمرار اهتمامها بالنواحي اللغوية، وهذا افضى إلى سلسلة من المقالات حول النصوص الهامة والنقوش الجديدة، وقد كانت كاثرين دوبياس- لالو (Catherine Dobias-Lalou) مسؤولة أيضا منذ عام 1988على قسم  (Cyrénaïque et Afrique Mineure) في مجلة (Épigraphique in the Revue des Études Grecques). كما كان لكل من جيانفرانكو باتشي (Gianfranco Paci) وسيلفيا ماريا مارينقو(Silvia Maria Marengo) دوراً في تطوير الدراسات المتعلقة بنقوش الإقليم.  حيث يعود فضل الأول لعمله في هذا المجال ولمنشوراته المتضمنة نصوص جديدة، كما يعود فضل مارينقو لعملها الأساسي المعنون بـ (Lessico delle iscrizioni greche della Cirenaica) لعام 1991 بالإضافة إلى العديد من المقالات حول النقوش القديمة والجديدة. ودرست ايضاً المؤرخة وعالمة البرديات لوتشيا كريسكولو (Lucia Criscuolo) كيرينايكي بسبب اهتمامها بالفترة البطلمية  للإقليم وأسهمت في تفسير معظم نقوش كيريني التاريخية المهمة.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">في أعقاب الثورة يبدو أن ليبيا  أصبحت تواجه "فترة تغييرلا نظير لها" وكان "الأمل كبير جداً في هذا" وأنها تكون قد "جلبت المزايا الجديدة لعلم الآثار والسياحة على حد سواء، وأن هذا’ يؤدي إلى ‘درجة من الوعي العام للتاريخ والآثار بين الليبيين أنفسهم الذين لم تتح لهم في السابق فرصة المشاركة’ [Kenrick 2013: 17]. انطلق مشروع IGCyr في نفس الفترة ذاتها و بالروح نفسها.</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">وكانت الخلاصة أن "كل شيء غير مؤكد للغاية منذ عام 2013، والبعثات الأثرية مستحيلة، ومعظم البعثات الدبلوماسية الأجنبية مغلقة أو انتقلت إلى بلد آخر؛ لكن العلماء الذين يُمنعون من زيارة ليبيا يمكنهم تقييم عملهم في هذه المرحلة، ويسعون على جعله متاحًا بشكل كامل أكثر من أي وقت مضى، على أمل توفير مورد غني للمنح البحثية الليبية في المستقبل". (إعداد: أليس بينسيفيني. مراجعة: شارلوت روشي. ترجمة: منى عبدالحميد).</p>
                    <p xml:lang="ar">ملحق 2023: بعد مضي اثني عشر عامًا على ثورة 2011 لا يزال الوضع في ليبيا غير آمن، وأعضاء مصلحة الآثار مخلصون للغاية لمهمتهم في الحفاظ على الآثار، لكن التحدي كبير، حيث يجب عليهم النضال ضد الدمار بفعل البشر والطبيعة: فأعمال البناء الجديدة في المناطق المحمية نظريًا من قبل اليونسكو والحفريات غير المشروعة تشكل مصدر قلق دائم، في حين السماح لأعضاء البعثات الأجنبية بالبقاء لفترة محدودة للغاية فإنه لا يمكنهم المساعدة بقدر ما يريدون، ومع ذلك، وبمساعدة تقنيات الاتصال الحديثة لم تنقطع الاتصالات أبدًا، ولا يزال التعاون نشطًا، مما أدى إلى نشر منشورات في مجلة االمصلحة (ليبيا القديمة)، ولم يكن التعاون بين البعثات الأجنبية أكثر فعالية مما كان عليه في تلك السنوات الصعبة، كما يشهد على ذلك الإنجاز الحالي. وقد أدت الرغبة في المساهمة بشكل مشترك في بحوث النقوش حول ليبيا إلى إنشاء شبكة دولية (شبكة أبحاث النقوش الليبية Libyan epigraphy Research Network: [رابط إلى LERN]) التي تتجاوز إطار InsLib السابق وتهدف إلى ضمان استمرارية المجموعة ومحتوياتها وتحديثها التدريجي على أساس تطوعي.</p>
                    
                <p xml:lang="ar">Alice Bencivenni (rev. Charlotte Roueché; translated by Muna Abdelhamed)</p></div>                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
